<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The armies remembrancer. Wherein they are presented with a sight of their sinnes and dangers. And also with a Scripture expedient for their preservation. / By a cordiall friend to the kingdomes welfare, Rr.</title>
            <author>Rr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E537_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14971</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858739</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858739</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164849</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92055)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164849)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 83:E537[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The armies remembrancer. Wherein they are presented with a sight of their sinnes and dangers. And also with a Scripture expedient for their preservation. / By a cordiall friend to the kingdomes welfare, Rr.</title>
                  <author>Rr.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34, p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Stephen Bowtell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 4th 1648". The 9 in 1649 has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164849:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Armies Remembrancer.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN They are preſented with a Sight of their <hi>Sinnes</hi> and <hi>Dangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo with a Scripture Expedient For their <hi>Preſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL. 2.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Remember therefore from whence thou art falne and Repent.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bernard in Dedic. Ecclae. Serm. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Non miremini fratres, ſi durius loqui videor,</l>
               <l>Quia Veritas, neminem palpat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>BY A <hi>Cordiall Friend to the Kingdomes welfare. Rr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Stephen Bowtell.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:164849:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:164849:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS EXCELLENCY THOMAS LORD FAIRFAX, Generall of the Parliaments For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to the Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Warre.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Much Honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving beene a ſorrowfull obſerver of your <hi>Unworthy walking,</hi> both for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly and of late; And taking notice of Gods diſpleaſure againſt you for it, ſo as not to be inhappied by a faithfull <hi>Admoniſher,</hi> or <hi>Remembrancer</hi> of your ſinner and dangers. I durſt not, finding the Holy-Ghoſt bringing this to my <hi>remembrance,</hi> to become a <hi>Remembrancer</hi> to you, bee <hi>diſobedient</hi> unto that <hi>Heavenly Viſion,</hi> by conſulting with fleſh and blood.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:164849:3"/>
            <p>Our bleſſed Saviour tells us, that in ſome caſes, if men ſhould prove ſtones and hold their peace, the ſtones ſhould prove men and immediately cry out, Luke, <hi>19.40.</hi> And truly did you but know me, as well as I doe my ſelfe, you would look upon mee as ſuch a miraculous <hi>Monitor,</hi> One, the ſtring of whoſe tongue is unlooſed, that never ſpake in this kinde before. But not upon the ſight of the murther of <hi>Craeſus,</hi> but of the utmoſt <hi>cryſis</hi> of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, wherein you have involved your ſelves and the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Though the Sceane be altered, the Court turned into a <hi>Councell of Warre,</hi> and the <hi>Court Paraſites</hi> vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away, yet am I jealous over you with a Godly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, that it is your great unhappineſſe not to be ſo free from <hi>Flatterers</hi> and <hi>Flatteries</hi> as I could wiſh. But not <hi>knowing how to give flattering titles, leaſt in ſo doing, my Maker ſhould ſoone take me away.</hi> Iob. <hi>32.22.</hi> I have declined in what I humbly preſent your Lordſhip, and your Councell of Warre in what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth (as your <hi>faithfull Remembrancer.</hi>) Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe <hi>affirmative flatteries,</hi> which are too often ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in your eares by way of incouragement in this your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent undertaking; but alſo that <hi>Negative flattery,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the ſilencing, or extenuating the ſinnes and miſcarriages of thoſe whom by the Law of Love we are bound to deale faithfully withall.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:164849:3"/>
            <p>Your Lordſhip and Councell well know, that in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications that <hi>Engeneer</hi> is a Traytor that conceales or leſſens a places weakneſſe, and he is no leſſe to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that ſhall with a negative flattery, conceale or exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate the ſinnes and miſcarriages of ſuch perſons, as may indanger the publique ſafety.</p>
            <p>I have therefore, in the integrity and ſincerity of my heart, for prevention of thoſe miſeries and calamities that are like to come upon your ſelves and the Kingdome, by your meanes, indeavoured by a ſound conviction to make you ſenſible that there are in you, even in you, ſinnes againſt the Lord your God, of which you are guilty, either <hi>actually,</hi> or <hi>acceſſarily, 2</hi> Epiſt. <hi>John. 11.</hi> And becauſe they are ſuch as have beene committed in the ſight of the Sunne, <hi>before all;</hi> therefore I have remembred and reproved you <hi>before all, that others may feare, 1</hi> Timothie, <hi>5.20.</hi> Wherein as I come not out againſt you, ſhod with <hi>indignation and ſcorn, being pleaſed</hi> to pour contempt vpon you, as you know who, <hi>(Sedg)</hi> nor yet with Lilburnian language, <hi>but with a ſpirit of meekeneſſe to reſtore you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So doe I hope for, and earneſtly deſire your favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptance and candid interpretation, Beſeeching your <hi>patience</hi> to read over, and ponder, what I have ſincerely and ſeriouſly propounded for yours and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, and your <hi>pardon</hi> for any un-intended fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb facs="tcp:164849:4"/>of mine in my expreſsions. And having by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er put this blunt weapon into an Omnipotent hand, that can make it cut indeed: I bow my knees to the Father of our Lord Jeſus, that bee would grant you according to the riches of his glory, to be ſtrengthened with all might by the ſpirit in the inward man, that ſo you may conquer your preſent temptations, and be recovered out of Satans ſnare, into which he hath brought you by transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe into an Angell of Light, even ſo prayeth, againe and againe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble Servant in the Lord,</hi> Rr</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:164849:4"/>
            <head>THE ARMIES REMEMBRANCER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EEing under a ſad Apprehenſion, of the great indignation, and diſpleaſure of <hi>our God,</hi> who manifeſts himſelf to bee a <hi>Conſuming fire,</hi> not only by permitting, the beginning, but the continuance of theſe cruell, and bloody civill Warres amongſt us. Being alſo much affected with a tender ſenſe, of the glory of our gracious God, and the honour of his bleſſed Goſpel, which ſuffereth much by your preſent miſcarriages, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truely touched with an unfeigned deſire of yours, and the Kingdoms welfare, and preſervation, which are exceedingly indangered, by your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaintlike practiſes, having alſo a clear viſion of that confuſion, that is like to come upon you, and this miſerable Kingdome by your means, except ſpeedily prevented.</p>
            <p>I am compelled to break through many <hi>intrinſecall</hi> and <hi>extrinſecall obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,,</hi> and though a very unable and unworthy inſtrument, to undertake ſo great a ſervice. Yet in the ſtrength of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt my Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to lay before you in all humility, ſincerity, and fidelity, what, I hope, he by his holy ſpirit, hath ſuggeſted unto my moſt ſad &amp; ſerious thoughts.</p>
            <p>But before I begin, I muſt neceſſarily doe theſe two things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to remove, what-ever may occaſion any prejudice againſt me, or the inſuing matter. And then <hi>Secondly,</hi> open my <hi>Commiſſion</hi> before you, that gives me warrant for this my enterprize.</p>
            <p>That I may doe the former, I muſt at this time walk rather by the <hi>Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> then the <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>Solemon</hi> his Son. His precept is, <hi>Let another man praiſe thee, and not thy ſelf, Prov.</hi> 27.2. But his Father <hi>practiſes</hi> to prevent a prejudice that was taken at his perſon, which was, to praiſe himſelf, and boaſt of his valour, and magnanimity, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.36. whoſe example I muſt ſo farre follow, in the commendation of my ſelf to you, being a ſtranger, as I may preſent the integrity and ſincerity of my affections towards your perſons (though not your ſins) as you are Souldiers and Saints by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which I have not only teſtified, before God and man in my prayers and Petitions for your Modellizing, but could produce many comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evidences that I have upon Record, of Gods hearing my prayers for you, when you have been engaged about his work in the field. And that you may not look upon me as an <hi>Apoſtate Round-head,</hi> in referrence to your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:164849:5"/>ſelves. I could produce witneſſes, that could teſtifie, that I have not been wanting in ſhewing my reſpects, and affections even ſince your firſt grand diſobedience (of which I ſhall humbly minde you by and by) All which and more, I could ſpeak to this end, that I might prepare your hearts and eares to receive without prejudice, what I have to propound, as comming from a Chriſtian, a Friend one that loves you, and deſires your welfare.</p>
            <p>And now in the next place, that I may ſhew you my <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> to bear me out in this my enterprize, beſides that call that I have from your ſelves in your Remonſtrance p. 4. <hi>The publique affairs in your hands being brought to the utmoſt Criſis of danger, calls upon every man to contribute what help he can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold I have it written in ſuch a book, as is more authentique then yours. <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy heart, thou ſhalt in any wiſe, rebuke thy neighbour, and not ſuffer ſin, on him.</hi> The morality of which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in regard of its equity and neceſſity, being of more force under the Goſpel, as the bonds of the Brother-hood, are now more ſtrong and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall. Beſides which, I find in the Goſpel, that we are not only to mourn for other mens ſins, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.18. but to reprove them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11. And that by the communion of Saints, we are not only to exhort and admoniſh one another, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.14. But that it is the duty of all that are ſpirituall, to reſtore thoſe that are overtaken with a fault, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.4. That they may be ſet in joynt again after a diſlocation.</p>
            <p>Now that you may be reſtored, &amp; ſet in joynt again, I ſhall preſent you with a <hi>Scripture expedient,</hi> by which you may be recovered out of that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous condition in which you have involved your ſelves and the whole Kingdom, in walking by <hi>providence</hi> without a <hi>precept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe that it is more then evident, that by thoſe great Victories and Succeſſes wherein God hath uſed you to be inſtruments for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Your hearts with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziahs,</hi> are lifted up to your own deſtruction, (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.16.) and of the Kingdom: Medling with thoſe matters and affairs, for which you have no more Commiſſion, then hee had for the Prieſts Office.</p>
            <p>I ſhall preſent you with a <hi>Hiſtory</hi> out of the trueſt <hi>Chronicle,</hi> wherein, if you will but weigh it, as I have done, you ſhall find, That which may cure you of your ſpirituall Tympany. As firſt, <hi>That ſucceſſe in Civill warre, to prevaile over our Brethren by the Sword, is not alwayes a ſigne of the Conquerours Saintſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That Conquerours that have found good ſucceſſe in the field, are very backward to beleeve that they are Sinners,</hi> And</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That a ſound Conviction of it, that there are ſins in a prevailing party over their Brethren, is an excellent expedient, to alter cruell purpoſes and intentions, and beget a brotherly union.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:164849:5"/>
            <p>Now becauſe that I deſire nothing more then that you may parallell that <hi>Army</hi> in the Hiſtory, both in the change of your <hi>purpoſes,</hi> and deſiſting from your <hi>practiſes,</hi> as they did upon a <hi>ſound Conviction.</hi> I ſhall a little am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie the following <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and become not only your <hi>Remembrancer,</hi> but <hi>Obſervator</hi> alſo, for want of a Better: Becauſe that our <hi>Odeds,</hi> our Prophets that ſhould come to you with the Meſſage I now bring you; are like to have but little acceptance; Becauſe you are not only apt to queſtion their Commiſſion, whether lawfull Miniſters, but muſing as you uſe, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, it might come from ſelf-intereſts, and by-reſpects.</p>
            <p>To detain you no longer therefore from this ſtory; you ſhall find it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.6. There wee read of a cruell warre which ended in a bloody ſlaughter, made upon the people of <hi>Judah,</hi> by <hi>Pekah</hi> the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (who all came out of the loyns of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and were all one Kingdome, till through ſin ſeperated and rent aſunder) by whom was ſlain in <hi>Judah,</hi> one hundred and twenty thouſand in one day, which were all valiant men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had forſaken the Lord God of their fathers, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. At which time the Kings Son was ſlain, and two of his Councellors, and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand women, ſons and daughters, were plundred, and brought captive to <hi>Samaria:</hi> But in the midſt of this great victory, and conqueſt over their brethren, had they an <hi>Euge</hi> from their Maſter? was it looked upon as that which called for a ſolemne day of thanks-giving? No ſuch matter, for behold, a Prophet of the Lord was there whoſe name was <hi>Oded,</hi> and he went out before the Hoaſt that came unto <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſaid unto them; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> becauſe the Lord God of your fathers was wrath with <hi>Judah,</hi> he hath delivered them into your hands, and yee have ſlaine them with a rage that reacheth up to heaven, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. and now you purpoſe to keep under the children of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for bond-men and bond-women unto you.</p>
            <p>Now if you wil conſult with the ſtory, you ſhal ther ſee by what argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he diverts them from this cruell purpoſe of theirs, to proſecute this victory with a cruell captivity; Saith he, <hi>But are there not with you, even with you, ſins againſt the Lord your God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This interrogation begot a ſound conviction, that they notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſucceſſes, were ſinners as well as their brethren.</p>
            <p>But how? by a particular application of ſin unto them with a double interrogation; <hi>Are there not with you, even with you,</hi> implying <hi>how hardly thoſe which are victorious and ſucceſſefull will bee convinced of their ſinfullneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had not the Prophet <hi>Oded</hi> come with this ſeaſonable conviction, they might have been puffed up with pride and ſelf-conceitedneſſe at their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and have looked upon their conquered and captivated brethren, as thoſe <hi>Jewes</hi> did upon the <hi>Galileans</hi> whoſe blood <hi>Pilat</hi> had mingled with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164849:6"/>their ſacrifices, <hi>to be greater ſinners then themſelves.</hi> 
               <q>They would have <hi>ſaid,</hi> oh, theſe vile wretches, theſe curſed <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> theſe having forſaken the Lord God of their fathers, are therefore juſtly delivered as a prey into our hands, who are more righteous then they, Their <hi>King</hi> would have <hi>intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced idolatry,</hi> Or at leaſtwiſe <hi>innovations</hi> in the <hi>worſhip</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> of God, and therefore when he went unto <hi>Damaſcus</hi> to ſtrengthen himſelfe by the King of <hi>Aſſiria,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.1. he there ſaw an alter, with which he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amored, and by it corrupted the worſhip and ſervice of God, And <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rijah</hi> his <hi>Cheife Prieſt</hi> was as forward in adulterating the ſame as he, <hi>v.</hi> 16. And all the people were like their Prieſt, <hi>all had forſaken the Lord God of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and turned Apoſtates.</q> But it appeareth that upon this ſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, by <hi>Odeds</hi> interrogation, the pride of their ſpirits, upon this mighty ſucceſſe was much abated, their cruell purpoſes and intentions were changed. And therefore we read of no reply made unto it, no ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for evaſions to keep off the blow, not a word in the <hi>aggravation</hi> of their brethrens wickedneſſe, or by way of <hi>extenuation</hi> of their owne rage and cruelty with which they were charged by the Prophet. But to ſhew the tractability of convinced ſinners, the Heads of the people inſtead of <hi>arguing,</hi> they fell to <hi>acting,</hi> and that in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to the <hi>Army,</hi> that had been ſo <hi>victorious,</hi> and were now returned with ſuch a numerous company of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. They uſe no carnall reaſonings, they conſult not with fleſh and blood, <hi>Wee muſt not diſcourage the Souldiery, they will not ingage for us another time.</hi> No, But in the 12. <hi>v. certain of the Heads of the people</hi> (whoſe names are upon record to their eternall honor) <hi>ſtood up againſt them, that came from the war, and ſaid, you ſhal not bring in the Captives hither. But yet to teach us,</hi> that <hi>as</hi> they which are convinced of ſins themſelves will valiantly oppoſe ſin in others. So they are tender of giving any ground of juſt offence, or ſhowing wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in their oppoſition; therefore they do here give them a reaſon of it, which containes an ingenious confeſſion of their own ſinnes, <hi>ver.</hi> 13 Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating further, That a ſound conviction of ſin, is accompanied with an ingenious confeſſion of ſin, And therefore ſay they, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>For whereas we have offended againſt the Lord already, you intend to adde more unto our ſins and our treſpaſſes.</hi> Concluding with all, that <hi>The cruelties of an Army towards their brethren by Nation or Profeſſion, ſhall be charged not onely upon themſelves, but thoſe that raiſed them.</hi> And therefore ſaid the Princes, and the Governours, <hi>you will adde unto our ſins, and our treſpaſſes.</hi> And let me but obſerve one thing more that theſe <hi>Heads</hi> of the children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> or <hi>Iſraell,</hi> they were not the <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> for it is ſaid expreſty, that theſe four Govenours, <hi>they ſtood up againſt them that came from the War,</hi> And therefore Mr. <hi>Will. Sedgwicks</hi> new Doctrine in his <hi>New view of the Army,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That when a State or Kingdom puts armes into Souldiers bards, they diveſt themſelves of their power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:164849:6"/>and conſequently by it become the peoples Repreſentatives:</hi> which he doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to prove in ſeverall Propoſitions. Are all anſwered by this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture inſtance, and the obedience of theſe <hi>Armed men</hi> that had no ſuch <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine,</hi> and by which is evident that in this <hi>point</hi> Mr. Sedgwick is <hi>as ſound in his judgement, as he was upon the day of Judgement it ſelfe.</hi> It appearing I <hi>ſay</hi> in this ſtory, that the Governours and Head of the people, when the Army acted cruelly, and ſinfully, to provoke the Lord to anger, withſtood them, and oppoſed them in ſuch away, as declared they had not diveſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their authority, and therefore not as unto their Equalls do they fall a <hi>praying</hi> and <hi>beſeeching</hi> them. Nor as to their Superiours in power to Petition them. But as to thoſe that were ſtill under their command, they ſpeak in the Imperative Moode: <hi>You ſhall not bring in the Captives hither, for whereas we have offended againſt the Lord already, you do intend to adde more unto our ſins, and our treſpaſſes, for our treſpaſſe is great, and there is fierce wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>Now follow the effects of this ſound Conviction, both upon the <hi>Army</hi> and the <hi>Princes,</hi> for they are diſtinguiſhed by the Holy ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt obſerve the ſucceſſe of it upon this ſucceſſefull Army to whom by <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> it was directed, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>But are there not with you, even with you, ſins againſt the Lord your God,</hi> v, 11. with which the <hi>Civill Magiſtrate</hi> concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, as I have ſhewed you, ſo prevailed upon the <hi>Armie,</hi> that they neither pretend to <hi>Salus populi,</hi> they affirm not, all their Brethren have is theirs, that they have conquered them, they ſay not, have we not adventured our lives to get all this ſpoil and plunder, No, but they deny themſelves in that which is a Souldiers joy, to <hi>devide the ſpoil;</hi> and as a <hi>Preſident</hi> for all Souldiers to be at the command of thoſe that raiſed them, they ſubmit themſelves, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>So the armed men left the Captives, and the ſpoil before the Princes, and all the Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord being intended to put a period unto the troubles of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people, <hi>works a happy conformity in the Army to the commands of the Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to give us alſo a reſemblance to the life, of the ſincerity of that ſorrow that was in the Princes for what they had done amiſſe alſo, though they could not ſhew it by putting life again into the dead carkaſes of their ſlaughtered Brethren, yet they not only decline the intended cruelty of the Army: But <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>they ariſe up, and with the ſpoil cloath all that were naked of their captived Brethren,</hi> and having comfortably reſteſhed them, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn them home again in peace and liberty. And I doe not find after this Reconciliation, by the aforeſaid expedient applyed unto them that were the Conquerors, that there were ever after any more <hi>Civill wars</hi> between <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Jadah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus now having preſented you with a Story which doth in part
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164849:7"/>gratifie your deſire, <hi>Remon. p.</hi> 27. of a people given up unto a <hi>prepoſterous and ſelf-deſerting way,</hi> ſo as to part with their Priſoners and plunder, and be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from a cruell deſign; But doth fully preſent you with a Scripture <hi>Expedient</hi> not only for the compoſing of our Diviſions and ending this civill War, but in particular moſt uſefull to ſtay you in this your ſinfull progreſſe, and to alter your purpoſes and intentions declared in your Remonſtrance. To which end I ſhall as your Remembrancer, <hi>remember you from whence you are fallen,</hi> and into what condition, and by propounding <hi>Odeds</hi> Interrogation, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring you to a <hi>ſound conviction.</hi> That there are <hi>in you, even in you, ſins</hi> againſt the Lord your God.</p>
            <p>Are there not <hi>with you,</hi> even <hi>with you,</hi> That doe profeſſe your ſelves to be the <hi>Saints</hi> of the LORD, and the <hi>children of the moſt High;</hi> The <hi>Illuminated</hi> ones of the LORD, and the <hi>children of the light,</hi> ſuch as are called with a <hi>holy calling;</hi> to be conformable unto <hi>your head,</hi> in <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, meekneſſe, ſelf deniall, contempt of the world, and ſaithfullneſſe in your truſt.</hi> Upon which your aforeſaid profeſſion, you were concluded to be ſuch as would prove the only faithfull ones in your <hi>truſt,</hi> and without all queſtion be <hi>obedient</hi> unto the Authority of thoſe that raiſed you, and <hi>put the ſword into your hands.</hi> But are there not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>with you, you,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sinnes.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience-waſting, and land-deſolating ſins, as the ſame root is uſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they ſhall not be deſolate: <hi>Againſt the Lord your God,</hi> againſt him in whom you profeſſe ſo much <hi>propriety,</hi> and ſpeak with ſo much boaſting of his <hi>preſence with you,</hi> and your intimate familiarity, communion, and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him: Are there not <hi>with you,</hi> even with <hi>you,</hi> ſins againſt the Lord your God; againſt him <hi>Abſolutely,</hi> and againſt him <hi>Relatively?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolutely,</hi> and <hi>Immediately,</hi> againſt his <hi>holineſſe,</hi> againſt his <hi>truth,</hi> againſt his <hi>free grace,</hi> againſt his <hi>glory,</hi> againſt his <hi>Goſpell,</hi> againſt his <hi>mercies,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Relatively</hi> are there not in you, even in you ſinnes againſt the Lord your God, in Relation to 1. the <hi>King,</hi> 2. the <hi>Parliament,</hi> 3. the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> 4. the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> 5. the <hi>City,</hi> 6. all that doe <hi>profeſſe Godlineſſe;</hi> 7. and laſtly, in relation to your owne <hi>ſelves,</hi> and <hi>ſoules?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That there are <hi>in you,</hi> even <hi>in you,</hi> ſinnes againſt the Lord your God; under all theſe <hi>conſiderations</hi> (That ſo you may be brought unto a ſound conviction, and may bee reſtored, and ſet in joynt again,) I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by hard arguments, and ſoft words, to <hi>convince</hi> you from your <hi>owne Papers,</hi> your <hi>practizes,</hi> and declared <hi>purpoſes,</hi> by all which it will <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,</hi> (that though by many you have beene moſt miſerably flattered; <hi>yet</hi> beſides thoſe manifeſt fruits of the fleſh, which are predominant in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164849:7"/>many of you, as <hi>Wrath, Strife, Sedition, Hereſie,</hi> Gal. 5.20. There are likewiſe many other <hi>ſinnes</hi> to be found amongſt you, that will declare that the <hi>Spots</hi> that are upon you, are not the <hi>ſpots of Gods Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I begin, beſides what I have already ſayd in my <hi>Preamble,</hi> to take off all prejudice, and that you might ſee into my heart, and behold the <hi>Riſe</hi> of this <hi>conviction,</hi> which is the trueſt love that can be <hi>manifeſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doe in the <hi>Bowels of Chriſt,</hi> not onely deſire your <hi>patience</hi> to reade over and over, what I am now to lay before you, (though it may ſeeme to be expence of <hi>time,</hi> and a diverſion from your weighty imployments) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (if effectuall) may ſave you a great deale of <hi>time,</hi> which otherwiſe you are like to ſpend, in the undoing of your ſelves, and the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>But as I deſire your <hi>patience</hi> to reade it; ſo to be <hi>Patients:</hi> And if to <hi>reſtore you,</hi> and ſet <hi>you in joynt againe:</hi> I ſhould handle you hard to your feeling. Conſider I beſeech you, it is not intended to <hi>hurt you,</hi> but to <hi>helpe,</hi> and <hi>heale</hi> you: If the Lord Jeſus by the <hi>ligament</hi> of his <hi>convincing Spirit;</hi> be but pleaſed to <hi>binde on,</hi> that which I onely can <hi>apply</hi> to your diſlocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>I begin therefore with <hi>Oded,</hi> to aske you this queſtion: Are there not with you, even with you ſins againſt the Lord <hi>immediately?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not you who doe expreſſe ſo much bitterneſſe of ſpirit, againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as <hi>Apoſtates?</hi> Are not you guilty of Apoſtacy, both <hi>Dogmaticall</hi> and <hi>Morall?</hi> Have you not beene ſo farre from walking worthy of that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Lord hath given us from <hi>Prelaticall Perſecution,</hi> by <hi>holding faſt the forme of ſound Doctrine of Faith and Love.</hi> 2 Tim. 1.13. and that <hi>faithfull word you have beene taught;</hi> As <hi>not onely</hi> to be carryed about with every wind of Doctrine, to bring the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of faith unto the Barre of ſhallow and <hi>corrupt reaſon,</hi> that <hi>incompetent Judge;</hi> And to <hi>diſguſt</hi> and diſlike thoſe Ancient Truths of Humiliation for ſinne, and mortification of the ſame; but alſo from theſe beginnings of <hi>Dogmaticall Apoſtacy,</hi> into ſmall <hi>errours,</hi> proceeding unto ſuch as doe race thoſe very <hi>Fundamentall Poynts,</hi> and <hi>Principles of Religion,</hi> which have the greateſt influence into <hi>practicall Holineſſe:</hi> Therein verifying Mr. <hi>John Goodwins</hi> aſſertion, in his booke of <hi>juſtification,</hi> in his Preface to the <hi>Reader</hi> Page 13. (ſayes he) <hi>Lots plea for Zoar, is it not a little one, is at no hand to be admitted for the ſparing of any errour? A ſmall errour cannot lightly be favoured, or connived at; but that great errours will be comprehended in the Indulgence:</hi> Oh Brethren I beſeech you be but ſerious in a ſelfe <hi>reflection</hi> in this particular, who by Sathans ſubtlety and ſophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry are ſo beguiled, as that though your Gold be turned into Tynne, your Silver into Droſſe, Truth into Errour, Verity into Here is; yet to conclude, your condition was never better, and therefore doe account
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:164849:8"/>thoſe <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians</hi> your greateſt Enemies that doe oppoſe you: Eſpecially in your endeavoured for <hi>Act of</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tolleration.</note> 
               <hi>Indemnity,</hi> for all <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> that ſhall depart <hi>from the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall forbeare in this place interrogating whether there are not in <hi>you</hi> ſins againſt the Lord <hi>your God;</hi> Not onely by your <hi>misbeleefe,</hi> in point of <hi>Errour</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> but by your <hi>unbeleefe,</hi> the univerſall Cauſe or <hi>Mother</hi> of that <hi>Morall</hi> Apoſtacy you are guilty of, becauſe I ſhall have occaſion to mind you, both of that and your abuſe of the mercies, and providence of God by and by.</p>
            <p>And not to mind you at large of your grand, and <hi>Originall disobedience,</hi> unto the Commands of the Parliament, in <hi>Refuſing to disband</hi> May 1647. your ſurprizing and removing the <hi>Kings Perſon</hi> from <hi>Holdenby,</hi> without and againſt the Parliaments pleaſure or privity, and after that your mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching up againſt the Houſe, accuſing their Members, preſenting the Houſe with Meſſages, ſo full of arrogancy as was altogether inconſiſtent with <hi>humble Saints;</hi> preſcribing them a time, with menacing expreſſions to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer you before night, as is to be ſeen, in ſome of your printed Letters and Meſſages which are upon record to the ſcandall of Religion.</p>
            <p>I ſay not to mention or remember you of theſe any further then to bring you unto a <hi>ſound conviction</hi> of your unconformity unto the Rule of the word, and the example of your Saviour.</p>
            <p>Oh the ſinnes that are with <hi>you,</hi> even with <hi>you againſt the Lord your God:</hi> Even ſince as it was reported, (to the gladding of the hearts of many that were truely godly) that you did keepe a day of Humiliation for thoſe forementioned offences: <hi>Yea,</hi> even ſince you have found the Lord graciouſly preſerving you from being devoured by a <hi>fire</hi> of your owne kindling, from ruine and deſtruction, through thoſe late Inſurrections both in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> of both which you were the <hi>occaſion</hi> by your not <hi>disbanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beſeech you aske your ſelves this Queſtion: Are there not with you, even with you, <hi>ſins</hi> againſt the Lord your God? Have not you abuſed the late mercies of God to your ſelves, and this Kingdome; thoſe great Victories, and ſpeedy ſucceſſes with which God had crowned you for the Kingdomes good? Have not you croſſed that <hi>providence</hi> of his, by which as with a Sunne beame he writ his gracious intentions towards this Kingdome, in ending their troubles by a <hi>Treaty,</hi> having from ſo low a condition ſuddainely raiſed up our Repreſentatives to a capacity of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon Tearmes, both <hi>Honourable, ſafe,</hi> and <hi>profitable</hi> for themſelves, and the Kingdome? Have not you abuſed all by your <hi>practiſes,</hi> and <hi>purpoſes,</hi> declared in your Remonſtrance? That you have ſo; I ſhall onely be your <hi>Remembrancer,</hi> to remember you, of an <hi>objurgation,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:164849:8"/>with you, of a <hi>Prophet of your owne,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Sedgwick,</hi> who though a very <hi>unlikely inſtrument;</hi> yet in his <hi>Juſtice upon your Remonſtrance,</hi> in many places, God hath <hi>opened his mouth,</hi> as once he did <hi>Baalams Aſſe</hi> to reprove you: <hi>Though</hi> now in his <hi>New view,</hi> he would like that <hi>Prophets Animall</hi> carry you himſelfe, leſt you ſhould not move faſt enough into thoſe <hi>courſes,</hi> that are like to prove ſo <hi>deſtructive</hi> to your ſelves, and the <hi>Cauſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by the light he then had <hi>heare him,</hi> from the quick ſtirrings of his owne conſcience, who profeſſeth intimate acquaintance with your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes from the beginning, pag. 23. Remon. I ſay, nay I pray heare his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation with you, pag. 17. <hi>God hath beene gracious unto you, and reprieved you for a while from deſtruction, doe you thus abuſe it to harden your hearts to pride, malice, and wicked inſulting over your Brethren? Is this the uſe of your Victories to have opportunities to doe more miſchiefe, and ſo treaſure up wrath for your ſelves, for all that you lay upon others you provide it, and ſtore it up for your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſides this abuſe of Mercies, Victories, and ſucceſſes, are there not with you, even with you ſinnes againſt the Lord? Are you not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull of his powerfull and providentiall care for you? Is it not your unbeliefe, (that gathers ſtrength in Chriſts abſence) that hath ſet your ſinnefull feares on worke, your corrupt ſelfe-love, and carnall policy? Why elſe have you taken hold of ſuch ungodly meanes, as now you uſe; though covered with ſpecious pretences in your Remonſtrance? You there pretend unto juſtice, and that againſt the Kings Perſon, as the moſt Capitall Offendor: But let me be your Remembrancer, of what is ſaid to it by a Prophet of your owne. Juſtice on Rem. p. 42. <hi>'Tis not Juſtice you deſire, it appeares ſo to your blinde and deceived hearts; but in the face of God it appeares farre otherwiſe: But the ſearcher of hearts will deale otherwiſe with you, and ſhew you what is within you, and diſcover the falſehood and injuſtice of your ſpirits.</hi> 43. <hi>Your Justice, 'tis but a bare name, or a Heathen covering borrowed from men to hide your ſhame, your malice, your unbeliefe, feare, and ſuch like mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous luſts, A cunning way to remove adverſaries, to take away thoſe that ſtand in your way, and paint them over with the names of Juſtice, ſecurity to the Publique In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and ſo Act them in the face of the Sunne.</hi> For the Lords ſake ponder this ſeriouſly, with his inſtance following, and be not deceived, for God will not be mocked. Oh take heede you that profeſſe the knowledge of God in his Attributes, and ſhould hold forth a <hi>conformity</hi> unto him in your converſations, to thoſe that are <hi>communicable,</hi> as his <hi>justice</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> how you plead <hi>juſtice</hi> for a cloake of maliciouſneſſe, and to ſinne ſo againſt his providence, as to make it to be the Father, not onely of your former perfidiouſneſſe and treachery againſt the Perſon of the King; but of your preſent intentions to doe juſtice upon him, which will appeare,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164849:9"/>pag. 24. where you ſay, <hi>God hath given him ſo clearly into your hands to do juſtice upon him;</hi> when the world knowes you have perfideouſly, and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly <hi>taken him</hi> in a ſnare: will you make the righteous Lord ſuch a one as your ſelves; in whoſe eſſence, or providence there is no iniquity. Did God <hi>give</hi> him into your hands, when you without the conſent of both Houſes <hi>tooke</hi> him away from <hi>Holdenby,</hi> and after your tampering with him at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and poſſeſſing him with a falſe, and notorious lye, to make him in a wet and tempeſtuous night, to leave that place to run into your Mouſe-trap, in which very act, was ſuch a concurrence of falſehood, and perfideouſneſſe, as never was committed, by any Profeſſors, and yet this muſt be fathered by you upon <hi>your God</hi> who loveth <hi>truth</hi> in the inward parts. You ſaying <hi>God</hi> having <hi>given</hi> him ſo clearly into your hands, when as the world knowes you have taken him, worthy Sirs, I beſeech you conſider this, leaſt God ſay unto you; <hi>Theſe things have you done, and I kept ſilence, you thought that I was altogether ſuch a one as your ſelves, But I will reprove you, and ſet your ſins in order before your eies,</hi> Pſal. 50.21.</p>
            <p>Having thus propounded <hi>Odeds</hi> queſtion, are there not with you, even with you, ſins againſt the Lord your God, againſt his <hi>truth,</hi> againſt his <hi>mercies,</hi> and againſt his <hi>providence; immediatly,</hi> or <hi>abſolutely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall but propound. <hi>Odeds</hi> interrogation: Are there not with you, even with you, ſins againſt the Lord your God <hi>Relatively,</hi> And that firſt in relation to the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſpeake not of any thing here, that you have done as Souldiers in the ſubduing of his forces, for which you were raiſed; and in which had you reſted, you had been the moſt renowned <hi>Champions</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi> But in referrence unto what you have acted out of your places, and ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and under this conſideration in relation unto the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Aske your Conſciences this queſtion, are there not with you, even with you <hi>ſins</hi> againſt the Lord in relation to the <hi>King,</hi> who are the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of hardning his heart? but your ſelves when you permitted his <hi>Chaplains</hi> to be about him, with the <hi>Service in its ſuperſtitious formality</hi> to be in uſe, after ſo long a weaning from them, by the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the <hi>Rarliament;</hi> who hath hardened his heart againſt all that do profeſſe <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thned him in his own way? But you with whom he hath <hi>converſed,</hi> and hath found to be ſo treacherous, perfideous and unconſtant; At one time crying <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> another time <hi>crucifige.</hi> At one time moving for the <hi>Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, of his Majeſties Perſon, his Queen and Royall iſſue to a condition of Safety, Honour and Freedom,</hi> Propoſall 14. 1647 <hi>July</hi> 2. Another time moving for the execution of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> that he may be brought to tryall for his life, when ſome of you perfideouſly got him under your power, under the pretence of the <hi>preſervation of his life</hi> from the <hi>Levellers,</hi> Oh, Chriſtians will
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:164849:9"/>not this bee required at your hands.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But in the next place, Are there not with you, even with you, Sins againſt the Lord your God in relation to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> if your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences be tender, they will accuſe you to purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Not to ſpeake largely of your former violence offered to the <hi>Parliament</hi> which you made to vote and unvote at your pleaſure in <hi>thoſe days,</hi> Oh bluſh and be aſhamed, at the comparing of the preface to your <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> and your following <hi>practiſes.</hi> You there profeſſe, <hi>your tender regard to the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and Freedomes of Parliament, on which your hopes of common Freedome, and right do ſo much depend: And yet your practiſes</hi> immediatly declare, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt breach of both, that ever was under the Sun.</p>
            <p>Oh deare Sirs, conſider this ſeriouſly; are there not with you, even with you, ſins againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who put the <hi>Sword</hi> into your hands. What is the Kings abuſe of <hi>truſt</hi> to yours. For firſt you not onely by your expreſſions in your <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> make this War for which they raiſed you to be offencive, <hi>pag.</hi> 27. When as the Parliament, by ſeverall Declarations, and in particular in a Covenant; which they took, and ingaged <hi>mee,</hi> with others in it, do propound this as that which we ſhould be perſwaded; <hi>or beleeve in our Conſciences, That the Forces raiſed by the two Houſes of Parliament, are raiſed and continued for their juſt defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subject againſt the forces raiſed by the King.</hi> But this is not all the <hi>wrong</hi> you have done them, for as you would <hi>pervert</hi> their <hi>ſence</hi> in raiſing you: ſo likewiſe their <hi>End,</hi> which was to ſubdue the forces raiſed by the <hi>King,</hi> but not to <hi>force,</hi> and ſubdue themſelves, and to bring them under the power of the Sword, and that in ſuch a way, as the Sun never ſaw, nor would, thoſe diſmall days of the 6 and 7 <hi>Decemb.</hi> being as darke and gloomey as the worke it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But beſides that execrable force and open violence upon many of the moſt cordiall and truly Godly Members of the Houſe of Commons, by which, the Priviledges and Freedome of Parliament were tranſcendent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broken by you. Beſides this I ſay, and your intentions by force to put a ſpeedy period unto this <hi>Parliament.</hi> I beſeech you ſearch into your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and ſeriouſly examin your ſelves, whether you have not a more ſinful and ſacrilegious <hi>deſign</hi> againſt the Parliament (having forced them) to rob and raviſh them of their <hi>Coercive power in ſpiritualls,</hi> in things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to <hi>Religion,</hi> though you doe pretend that you have faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated your <hi>Grievances</hi> with the <hi>Remedies:</hi> yet your diſſimulation is without compariſon, in that, though not a word in your Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, concerning <hi>Tolleration,</hi> as declaring it to bee the riſe or ground of theſe your preſent <hi>Commotions,</hi> yet is it evident, by your preſent agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:164849:10"/>That the <hi>Magiſtrats</hi> of your making ſhall neither have <hi>Coercive,</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictive</hi> power in matters of <hi>Religion;</hi> and that by <hi>Club-law</hi> you would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> of the fame which I beſeech you to weigh ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and conſider the <hi>guile</hi> and the <hi>guilt</hi> of this <hi>deſign</hi> which is aggravated by what you doe acknowledge, page 20. Your Remonſtrance: <hi>That it is the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments intereſt;</hi> in plaine engliſh that which doth <hi>belong to them,</hi> To <hi>protect and countenance Religions men, and godlineſſe in the power of it, to give freedome and inlargement unto the Goſpel, to take away thoſe corrupt formes of an outſide Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Church-government.</hi> All which by the abuſe of that power they have put in your <hi>hands,</hi> you would now wreſt out of their <hi>ſhires;</hi> which with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſinnes againſt the Parliament, in that <hi>horible contempt,</hi> that you have caſt upon them: If but brought home by a <hi>ſound conviction,</hi> muſt needs make you acknowledge in this reſpect, <hi>there are with you, even with you, ſinnes againſt the Lord</hi> your God in <hi>relation to the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But thirdly, are there not with you, even with you, ſins againſt the Lord your God in relation to the <hi>whole Kingdom?</hi> Beſides the miſeries contracted upon the Kingdom ſince your refuſall to disband, at the command of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in the extream expences, and charges you have drawn upon them, by taxes and free-quarter: wherein you have ſhewed but little publick-ſpirited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or love unto the <hi>Common wealth.</hi> Though you have pretended to a great deal of <hi>bleeding of ſoule,</hi> that you ſhould be forced to take <hi>Free quarter,</hi> for want of pay. But that your diſſimulation is great in this particular, and ſo your ſin anſwerable againſt the Kingdom. You have almoſt doubled the burthen even upon thoſe that would willingly have paid you the States pay, <hi>per diem,</hi> either for horſe or man, to be freed from ſuch troubleſome and uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gueſts.</p>
            <p>But alas! what is this to what you have done againſt the whole Kingdome in your late tranſactions? How doth this <hi>Remonstrance,</hi> demonſtrate that there are with you, even with you, ſins againſt the whole Kingdom? You doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> and that extremity of publich danger, hath put you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe extraordinary wayes you have taken. But hath the Kingdom, ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this their <hi>Publick danger,</hi> inveſted you with any power, to ſtir up theſe commotions in their behalf? Are you in the condition of <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> for the Kingdom? Why then doe you ſo deceitfully pretend unto publick dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, when as that by your walking, out of Gods way, you are like to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtruments of danger unto the Publicke as well as your ſelves? Hath the <hi>Kingdom</hi> called upon you, in their Names, to cry out for <hi>Jastice,</hi> to interrupt the <hi>Treaty,</hi> to muſter up ſo many Arguments againſt the goodneſſe and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, which you have preſented in ſo many ſheets of paper, in your <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance,</hi> containing more of the <hi>Serpents Subtlety,</hi> then the <hi>Doves Innocency?</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:164849:10"/>Are your <hi>Propoſals</hi> therein for the altering the fundamentall Conſtitutions of the Kingdome, are theſe <hi>injunctions</hi> laid upon you by the <hi>Originall of all power,</hi> as you pretend, the <hi>People</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome?</hi> Alas, they know none of theſe things, ſo as to approve of them, not one of a hundred will own what you doe ſet down for the <hi>Publick Intereſt,</hi> Nor ſubſcribe unto that <hi>Agreement</hi> that you ſpeak on, pag. 66. And yet ſuch is your Arrogancy, Injuſtice, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed Tyranny, that though but an inconſiderable part of the Kingdome, and that a diſeaſed one, but a Member of the body Politique, in compariſon of the whole, and that a diſlocated one, yet how cruelly would you indeavour to force the whole body of the Kingdome, to an <hi>agreement</hi> with your <hi>diſ-joynted part,</hi> to rack and torture their conſciences, with a ſubſcription unto your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Tolleration, and Confuſion; And yet without this <hi>Subſcription,</hi> though none can take away the Kingdomes liberties, without their <hi>perſonall,</hi> or <hi>repreſertatives</hi> conſent, yet have you ſo propoſed or rather impoſed it upon the Parliament in your <hi>remonſtrance,</hi> that none ſhall either elect their <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives,</hi> who ſhall not joyne in agreement to this ſettlement. page 66. or be <hi>Elected unto any office, or place of publique truſt without expreſſe accord, and ſubſcriptions to the ſame,</hi> page 67.</p>
            <p>Certainely Sirs, your injuſtice and cruelty to the Kingdome will cry loud in the eares of God againſt you. Eſpecially conſidering the aggravations of it, even in relation to the Kingdome that you deale ſo injuriouſly withall.</p>
            <p>That when a Kingdom by the firſt Remonſtrance of their Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in Parliament, made ſenſible of their danger, both in regard of Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and Secular Intereſts, and withall aſſured in the ſame, of the reallity of their intentions to prevent it, without the <hi>change</hi> of the frame of the <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Government,</hi> or letting looſe the <hi>golden reines</hi> of the Eccleſiaſticall, and upon ſatisfaction given by the Magiſtracy and Miniſtery, of the lawfulnes of oppoſing the Kings Arbitrary power, without the breach of the Oath of Allegiance unto his Perſon, as is evident by the firſt Proteſtation, <hi>May</hi> 5. 1641 the chief Subject of it being to <hi>maintain and defend Religion, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royall Perſon, Honour, and Estate, according to the duty of our Allegiance, as alſo the power and priviledges of Parliament, with the lawfull Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subject.</hi> And the <hi>ground of it</hi> being but a ſuſpicion of <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſubvert the fundamentall Laws, and to introduce the exerciſe of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary and Tyrannicall government, by moſt pernicious and wicked counſells and plots,</hi> amongſt which is inſtanced, their <hi>jealouſie</hi> of being forced by that Engliſh <hi>Armie</hi> then on foot.</p>
            <p>Which were then ſtrong Arguments to incourage the Kingdome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to enter into that <hi>ingagement,</hi> and after that to proceed further, to the oppoſition of the Kings forces in a defenſive wat, which in the ſecond vow was clearly expreſſed to be their intent of raiſing Forces, Viz. <hi>For the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:164849:11"/>of the true Proteſtant Religion, and Liberties of the Subject, againſt the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces raiſed by the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That now the <hi>Forces</hi> ſo raiſed by the <hi>Parliament</hi> for the Kingdoms good, ſhould after crowned with ſucceſſe by the Lord of Hoaſts, not only refuſe to <hi>disband,</hi> but as aforeſaid march up, and bring that evill upon the Parliament which by their own and the Kingdoms Proteſtation they feared from the Northern Army; Viz <hi>A Rape and Force upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that by your continuance in Armes, ſhould occaſion, <hi>as</hi> through the Activity of Malignant Spirits, <hi>ſo</hi> generally, through the ſence the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and the Kingdom had of their unſupportable burthen by your means, to be again imbroyled in a <hi>New War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein as you are not guiltleſſe, as in the occaſion of the war: So chiefly, in the interruption of that <hi>peace</hi> ſo generally deſired.</p>
            <p>And therefore when as the poor Kingdom torn and rent with civill wars, weary of its burthen, ſeeing no hopes of ending by the Sword, but that <hi>one extremity did daily beget another,</hi> had prevailed by their Petitions to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for a Treaty which was obtained, and in it ſuch a progreſſe made, as that the Parliament notwithſtanding your Remonſtrance, voted The Kings laſt Anſwer to be a good foundation for a Peace and ſettlement.</p>
            <p>Yet who hath diſappointed the Kingdoms hopes but you, not only inveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the Treaty as juſt, or ſafe for the Parliament to mannage, though you durſt when time was preſume to <hi>Treat with him your ſelves,</hi> when it was <hi>unquestionably</hi> unjuſt for you, having no delegation from the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> or its <hi>Repreſentatives,</hi> but alſo by the power of the Sword to interrupt it, without and againſt the conſent of the oppreſſed Kingdom, whoſe cry I fear is gone up to heaven againſt you.</p>
            <p>Beſides which with your interpoſition in the affaires of the Kingdome, in taking the work out of the hand of the Kingdoms Repreſentative. Have you not by your late practiſes not only endeavoured, but acted thoſe iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which you were only <hi>raiſed</hi> to prevent in the <hi>forces</hi> raiſed by the <hi>King.</hi> namely, the ſubverting of the fundamentall Laws of <hi>England,</hi> the power and priviledges of the Parliament, and the lawfull Liberties of the Subject?</p>
            <p>And all under the colour of laying new <hi>foundations</hi> for <hi>freedome,</hi> which in the language of Juſtice <hi>Sedgwick; have little of right, freedome, or common ſafety in them, being framed with reſtect to your own private intereſt, why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doe you diſſemble with men holding forth a foundation to ſettle the Kingdom, when that you doe profeſſe your ſelves, to be appointed and called for breaking in pieces the powers of the world,</hi> page 48.</p>
            <p>But if there be any reall intentions in you of a ſettlement, (which your intimate friend doth much queſtion) that you may ſee what your private ſpirits, confident of their Abillity and Judgement for greateſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:164849:11"/>matters of State Policy, have produced to impoſe upon the Kingdome; I ſhall give you the deſcription of your intended Government, by Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Sedg.</hi> Not in his <hi>New View,</hi> but in his <hi>True View</hi> of the Army, p. 22. <hi>For your preſent forme of Government, it is ſuch a headleſſe Monſter, ſuch a boddy doddy, ſuch an all breech, ſo different from the Majeſty of God, and the Wiſdome of men, that it would fright ſolid and ſerious men to their Armes: If I ſhould fight againſt any thing, I ſhould fight againſt this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But more ſeriouſly, hoping that God will never permit you to erect, and ſet up a ſecond Fabrick, that falling ſo ſhort of the glory of the firſt Temple of our Government, ſhould fill all Spectators with <hi>watery eyes,</hi> and yet extreamely fearing, leſt that under all your pretences for juſtice, inſtead of any kinde of Government; you are laying the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of perpetuall miſery unto this Kingdome, both by <hi>inteſtine,</hi> and <hi>Forraigne troubles.</hi> Oh let <hi>Odeds</hi> interrogation take hold of your hearts; are there not with you, even with you ſinnes againſt the Lord your God, not onely in Relation unto the King and Parliament, but in Relation unto the whole Kingdome?</p>
            <p>But in the fourth place, let me be your Remembrancer a little further, And with <hi>Oded</hi> aske you: Are there not with you, even with you, ſinnes againſt the Lord your God, not onely in relation to King, Parliament, and Kingdome; but alſo in relation to the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> the Famous City of <hi>London, the great aſſiſtant of the Parliament, Famous for its incouragement to the Parliament, in maintaining it, as was acknowledged by Mr. John Pym</hi> in his Speech to them, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 10. 1641.</p>
            <p>Not to ſpeake of its ſufferings in common with the Kingdome, by the meanes of your former diſobedience to the Parliament: Or to minde you at large of the contempt you poured upon the City ſhortly after, when you marched through the City as Conquerours, with Bayes in your hats, your poſſeſſing your ſelves of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> caſting out their Lievetenant, put in by the Parliament at their requeſt, impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and impriſoning by your meanes, ſome of their Aldermen, that were knowne to be of <hi>Publique Spirits,</hi> not <hi>inriching</hi> themſelves with the ruines of the Kingdome, together with ſome of the <hi>Common Councell,</hi> both for piety and ſtability to their Principles, <hi>Proteſtation, Vow,</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> without exception, charging the whole City with defection, and <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from the Parliament: I beſeech you ſeriouſly conſider, cannot they taxe you with <hi>unfaithfulneſſe,</hi> as well as King, Parliament, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Peruſe but your Letter ſent to them from Royſton, June 10. 1647. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you <hi>profeſſe you deſire no alteration of the Civill Government, nor that you ſeek to open a way unto licentious liberty, under pretence of obtaining eaſe for tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:164849:12"/>page 5. and doe not you <hi>profeſſe that when the State hath once made a ſettlement, you have nothing to ſay but to ſubmit, or to ſuffer.</hi> Do but compare your practices with this <hi>profeſſion</hi> made unto the City, and conſider, whether you have not much cauſe to be humbled; are not all your preſent practices in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Parliament, Kingdome, and City, made our of meaſure ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by acting ſo contrary unto your <hi>profeſſion.</hi> But beſides all this. Conſider I pray you, the <hi>feares</hi> and the <hi>dangers,</hi> which you have expoſed them unto in this your laſt expedition againſt the <hi>Parliament;</hi> not to ſpeake of your unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable demands for monies in ſuch vaſt ſummes, your menacing preſſing for your arreares, even for thoſe twelve moneths ſervice paſt, ſince the <hi>Vote</hi> of your disbanding; Is not your poſſeſſing your ſelves of the gates of the City, planting Ordinances againſt them, as in Black-friers and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; your violent ſeizing upon the perſon of their Shreive, Major Generall <hi>Browne.</hi> Are not theſe moſt injurious and unchriſtian carriages to the City.</p>
            <p>And beſides the unconceivable damage you have brought unto it by the decay of trade, and merchandizing, who knoweth what further danger may ariſe by quartering the Army thus amongſt them, Theſe things thus laid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and well weighed, muſt needs bring you to a <hi>ſound conviction,</hi> that there are with you, even with you, ſinnes againſt the Lord your God in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the City.</p>
            <p>Again, are there not with you, even with you, ſins againſt the <hi>Gedly, learned, and ſound Miniſters in the Kingdome.</hi> Are you not ſuch, as ſhew your ſelves to be <hi>deſpiſers</hi> of Chriſt, by <hi>deſpiſing</hi> his Meſſengers and Miniſters. Are not you ſuch as by your <hi>mockings</hi> and ſcorning of the Prophets, have provoked the Lord even till there be no remedy. What meaneth the horrible contempt you have caſt upon them, both by your words and actions. I ſpeake not of the <hi>Prelaticall Clergy,</hi> but of the Miniſters, who have now ſuffered both from <hi>them,</hi> and your <hi>ſelves,</hi> and find their laſt <hi>wounds</hi> deepeſt, becauſe received in the <hi>houſe of their friends,</hi> Doe not you ſhow your ſelves to be apoſtatized from them both <hi>dogmatically</hi> and <hi>morrally,</hi> both in your judgements and affections? How are thoſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> in which many of you delighted, and <hi>rejoyced</hi> in their <hi>light,</hi> now fleighted by you? are you not being puffed up with ſpirituall pride and conceitedneſſe, ready to thinke your ſelves ſo full of knowledge, ſo rich in gifts and parts, that you can <hi>reigne as Kings without them.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8. and are you not ſo taken with the Prieſts of your owne making of the loweſt of the people, and ſo enamered with your owne <hi>Buffe-coate Chaplaines,</hi> that the <hi>Black-coates,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> as you frequently in diriſion call them (ſuch as have the truth of their calling <hi>ſealed</hi> by the converſion of <hi>ſoules,</hi> are now decryed by you as <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that you could but ſee how wofully Satan hath beguiled you by this <hi>Stratagem,</hi> and brought you to bite the breſts that have ſuckled you, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:164849:12"/>being bewitched as were the <hi>fooliſh Galuthians,</hi> like fooliſh children, know not your own ſpirituall Fathers, by whom you firſt beleeved; Oh that the ſinfulneſſe of the <hi>cauſe,</hi> and the ſadnes of the <hi>effects</hi> might affect your hearts, for from this corruption in your judgements concerning the <hi>lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of their <hi>calling,</hi> you who formerly could have <hi>plucked out your eyes for them,</hi> are now ready to pluck out theirs; not only forſaking but oppoſing them, and that the <hi>more</hi> they ſhow their zeal for Chriſt, and love to you in oppoſing you in your <hi>Errors,</hi> and theſe your ungodly and unchriſtian courſes.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you Sirs, pardon me if I cry out for my Fathers; the <hi>charets of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof,</hi> when you would ſnatch them away from me, and the whole Kingdome in a fierie charet, I mean in your burning zeal againſt <hi>Tithes to paid any more,</hi> which that judicious Patriot in his Reaſons againſt the <hi>agreement</hi> ſaith himſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>I beleeve that taking away the Miniſtry of the Goſpel with their maintenance, lieth at the bottom of it.</hi> But admit this ſhould not be the <hi>bottome</hi> of it, this ſhould not lie at the <hi>root,</hi> to <hi>root</hi> them out, as being Antichriſtian; yet this will lie at the top as a viſible deſign to <hi>ſtarve them out</hi> of their Miniſteriall imployment, and either expoſe them with their, Families to beggery, or elſe to doe more, then <hi>leave the Word of God and ſerve Tables,</hi> (which the Apoſtles, though they could preach <hi>extempore,</hi> did account a great diverſion from their Miniſtry) and to goe dig for their <hi>living,</hi> and get it by the ſweat of their browes.</p>
            <p>Oh friends weigh theſe things ſeriouſly and conſider whether from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid premiſes you give not them occaſion to conclude that you are very unkind, and that you walk not as <hi>becommeth Saints</hi> in relation to them, and withall from what they may <hi>fear</hi> (by the Students you put into <hi>Sion Colledge,</hi> and other of your carriages towards them) may bring up the Reer againſt them, for their non conformity to their new Metropolitans: Thinke ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly whether you have not given them occaſion ſadlie to complain, <hi>That they have nouriſhed and brought up ſpirituall children, but they have rebelled againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to <hi>charge on,</hi> are there not with <hi>you,</hi> even with <hi>you</hi> ſins againſt the Lord your God in relation unto all that doe profeſſe <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> that are now divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into <hi>Independents, Presbiterians,</hi> and <hi>Interpendents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have not <hi>you</hi> cauſe with that Primitive Penitent, having offended the Church of God, to caſt down your ſelves in <hi>your</hi> thoughts at the feet of all Profeſſors of Religion, ſaying with him, <hi>Calcate me ſalem incipidum, Tread upon me unſavory Salt,</hi> Oh that God would but give you humble apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>your ſelves</hi> under this conſideration as having in <hi>you</hi> ſins againſt the Lord your God in relation to the <hi>Saints indeed,</hi> that not only thoſe Profeſſors of Religion that diſſent from <hi>you,</hi> but even againſt thoſe of <hi>your own party</hi> who are not groſſely corrupted in their judgements, and blinded with ſelf-intereſts,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:164849:13"/>as being in great places of <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>profit,</hi> but do all look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves as extreamly injured by your unwarantable walkings, and muſt needs withdraw from you, as <hi>brethren</hi> that walke <hi>inordinatly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was <hi>Davids</hi> prayer, that <hi>none that truſted in God might bee aſhamed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of him.</hi> But have not you filled the faces of Profeſſors of Religion with <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>bluſhing. Becauſe</hi> that finding <hi>neceſſity</hi> for <hi>ſinning</hi> but a ſinfull plea, they know not how to uſe it to their upbraiding adverſary, either in your behalfe, or their owne; and therefore becauſe of <hi>you</hi> muſt hang down their heads: But is this all, no, you have not by your aforeſaid miſcarriages, filled their faces with ſhame, but made them <hi>ſtink, Gen.</hi> 34.30. they may truly ſay with <hi>Jacob, you have troubled me, and made me to ſtinck a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the inhabitants of the land, and being few in number they ſhall gather them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together againſt me, and ſlay me.</hi> Oh ſirs! let this take hold on <hi>your</hi> hearts, the wrong you have done to your brethren, by expoſing them to danger.</p>
            <p>I doe confeſſe that formerly the oppoſition that was made againſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors was for their holineſſe indeed, becauſe that they were ſuch, as by their frequent attendance upon the Ordinances, their care to worſhip God in them, according to his own will, their mortification and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world, their ſobriety and not conformity to the vaine faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the time; and their not daring to do <hi>evill</hi> that <hi>good</hi> might come of it, <hi>did</hi> judge, and condemne the world even by their actions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though they were perſecuted and oppoſed, yet their perſecutors ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by hand or tongue, could not from their exact &amp; innocent walking, but be convinced in their conſciences, that thoſe whom they did <hi>perſecute</hi> were more righteous then themſelves, &amp; never did them any perſonall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. But is not in theſe times, the naturall enmity of the world exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through the iniquities of many profeſſors, when inſtead of thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious effects of the power of godlines, which did imbelliſh &amp; adorn Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: Contrary luſts are more viſible, ſuch as a libertie to follow the vaine faſhions of the times, to be free and liberall in the uſe of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, feeding without feare as <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeakes, to be ſelfe ſeekers in time of calamatie, unfaithfull in promiſes and truſt, and yet for all this to bee exceeding proud and cenſorious, concluding themſelves to be the onely Saints, and therefore are to have the <hi>high places of the earth,</hi> as the only fit men for places of Government, and none ſo zealous for the execution of juſtice; whilſt they break out into ſuch courſes, as are full of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; and tend to the ruine of others as well as themſelves?</p>
            <p>I beſeech you Sirs weigh this ſeriouſlie and conſider, whoſe caſe this is that I have propounded, whither there be not in <hi>you,</hi> even in <hi>you</hi> ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord your God in relation to all that are <hi>godly,</hi> who upon the <hi>grounds aforeſaid</hi> are expoſed unto the <hi>irritated</hi> enmity of the men of the <hi>world</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:164849:13"/>though M. <hi>Peters</hi> ſay it is only <hi>for a little holines,</hi> &amp;c. And though I hope that God wil take care of thoſe profeſſors, that ſhal profeſſe their preſent diſlike of your preſent practiſes and mourn for them, ſo as that they may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, if (God ſee it good for them) from that calamitie that ſhall come upon you, yet aſſure your ſelves, that without repentance <hi>you</hi> ſhall feele the juſtly exaſperated rage of the men of the world, and bee brought into a ſuffering condition, <hi>as evill doers;</hi> and where then will the ſpirit of glorie be to reſt upon <hi>you?</hi> you may peradventure by this argument think that I am too great a legaliſt, and may think your ſelves to be above all theſe feares, becauſe that you are Saints, and have your ſins forgiven <hi>you.</hi> But know that <hi>Aaron</hi> the Saint of the Lord, with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> though God forgave their ſins, yet he took vengeance of their inventions, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90.8. and therefore be not high minded but fear, leaſt God to vindicate his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to let the world know, that he ſtands not in need of the ſins of men, to preſerve his <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Cauſe, But that he is the Lord that loveth judgement, and hateth robbery for a burnt offering</hi> Iſa. 61.8. ſhould take vengeance on your inventions, by expoſing you unto a ſuffering condition, as evill doers that have invented, and do ſo ſtrongly urge and act for it, <hi>a Toleration,</hi> that you might keep your ſelves from a ſuffering condition, in relation to what you hold forth as <hi>truth,</hi> we have a memorable example in the book of Martiers of one, that could not burn for Chriſt, and yet to ſave ſome goods, his houſe being on fire was burnt and conſumed by it. The Lord give you in this your day to know the things that do belong unto your peace; and that you may prevent that danger and deſtruction which theſe practiſes will produce. For as there are in <hi>you</hi> ſins againſt the Lord your God as in relation to others, ſo unto your own ſelves; theſe your unwarrantable waies and actions if they ſhould not bring deſtruction up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kingdome, <hi>yet</hi> as I have already intimated, <hi>will</hi> without making your repentance as publicke as your offence, bring you unto ceraine ruin and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And that you may ſee the danger you have brought your ſelves in, as by all thoſe ſins of which I have been your Remembrancer: ſo in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, by your intended change of the Government both of Church and State, in oppoſition to King, Parliament and Kingdom. I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto your view, Mr. <hi>Henry Burtons</hi> two Sermons for God and the King, I ſhall onely give you his text with ſome part of its explication lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it to your own application.</p>
            <p>Prov. 24.21, 22. <hi>My ſon feare thou the Lord and the King. And meddle not with them that are given to change, for their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only remember you of the admonition, with his reaſon explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his own words.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:164849:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Meddle not with them which are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Meddle</hi> is not meant here that wee may not meddle at all, by way of reproofe, detection, conviction, impeading, or impeaching their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed courſes and practiſes that are given to change. But not meddle, that is, have no fellowſhip, ſide not, countenance not, approve not, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud not ſuch men in their evill waies; But who are theſe men we are admoniſhed of? <hi>Such as are given to change,</hi> the beſt Interpreters expound it of Innovations of Religion, or of the Republike. So <hi>Mercer</hi> and <hi>Lavater,</hi> and <hi>Pagnin</hi> renders it; Such as change and break the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, and of their Princes, and fall away from the feare of God and the King in their rebellious lives; but we need goe no further then our owne tranſlation which is very full, meaning it of all ſuch as are factious, ſeditious, given to change the Lawes of God and the King. page 6. 7.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Now is the reaſon of the admonition annexed, which is taken from the dangerous condition that thoſe that are given to <hi>change</hi> are obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto, the matter of their danger <hi>calamity and ruine</hi> ſet downe in its <hi>ſuddenneſſe</hi> in its <hi>certainty.</hi> It ſhall <hi>riſe,</hi> that is although they ſeeme to be ſo high, <hi>that are given to change,</hi> as to ſurmount all feare of dangers as trampling all under their feet, yet calamity ſhall riſe above them, and bring them to ruine as the Lord ſaith, <hi>Ier.</hi> 37.10. page 8. 2. It ſhall ariſe <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> and <hi>unexpectedly,</hi> that is, though there be no outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ruine to theſe men, but that all things proſper and ſeeme to be on their ſide, page 5. Yet <hi>who knoweth the ruine of them both;</hi> this is ſubject to ſundry interpretations, the gloſſe and Lyra (to both) to Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriticks, and thoſe that are ſeduced by them: <hi>Mercenus</hi> and <hi>Lavater,</hi> underſtand ruine of them both in an Active ſenſe, referring the ruine of thoſe that are given to change, to <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> who both ſhall bring ruine upon thoſe that are given to change. So that thoſe ring-leaders with their adherents and complices ſhall both fall and periſh together, and both <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> that is, the juſtice of Gods law, and mans law ſhall conſpire together to root them out. page 8.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus now having laid before you that from Mr <hi>Burtons explication</hi> of the Text, which if but mixed with faith, and applied, muſt needs be <hi>energeticall</hi> in its operation to change your <hi>purpoſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall goe on as your Remembrancer, having with <hi>Odeds</hi> interrogation indeavoured to convince you, that there are in you, even in you, ſinnes againſt the Lord your God, both abſolutely and relatively, in relation to King, Parliament, Kingdome, Miniſtery, City, with all that profeſſe godlineſſe. I ſhall proceed to minde you of ſome aggravating circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances with which ſome of your moſt publique ſins are cloathed, and alſo with ſome ſad effects of them,</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:164849:14"/>
            <p>As firſt, doe not you profeſſe in your Remonſtrance, page 4. <hi>You are not ignorant that rule of ſalus populi ſuprema lex, is of all others moſt opt to be abuſed or miſapplied;</hi> and indeed you ſhow wherein it may be abuſed, and how, moſt truly. But doth it not aggravate your guilt that you ſhould abuſe it in all thoſe kindes? The Lord give you tender conſciences, and then you will confeſſe that you have as truly abuſed it, as you have deſcribed how it may be done. For doe not your practices ſince the publiſhing of your Remonſtrance, together with what is in agitation by you, declare page 4. That notwithſtanding your <hi>pretences of publique danger, and the extremity thereof, that yet from evill intentions and an inordinate temper of ſpirit,</hi> you would breake thoſe bonds of law and Magiſtracy which you finde to reſtraine you. Beſides which, are not you <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> condemned of your ſelves, even out of the words of your owne mouths, as being defective; as in that which you your ſelves doe propound, muſt <hi>concur to their full juſtification that</hi> ſhall plead <hi>Salus populi,</hi> for you ſay he that ingageth, page 5. <hi>Vpon ſuch pretences, muſt do it really for publike ends, and but upon publike neceſſity, or extremity, and with a ſober ſpirit.</hi> But whether you are not unquallified in all theſe, I leave it to God, the World, and your owne Conſciences when awakened, to judge whether in your pleading of <hi>Salus populi,</hi> and your actings upon it, inſtead of <hi>reall publike ends,</hi> private intereſt, carnall feares, ambition, pride, an apprehenſion of your neglect in the Treaty; no aſſurance of pardon for your fore-mentioned practices againſt the King and Parliament, without and contrary unto commiſſion are not <hi>really your publike ends</hi> that put you upon this plea of <hi>Salus populi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it is not for <hi>publike neceſſity and extremity,</hi> (except to beget it) you have the cry of the whole Kingdome againſt you for it, and if you have the quallification of the <hi>agent, a ſober ſpirit</hi> for your iuſtification, let your actions upon it, in the violent ſeiſing upon the perſons of ſo many grave godly and publike Patriots of the Kingdome, with horrible indignitie by turning them into Hell, with ſuch unheard of taunts and reproaches, as are upon record in your Moderate Intelligencer that came out the tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following, plead for you. Theſe things I ſay doe cry loud in the eares of God to whom you have appealed, and as you acknowledge <hi>hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a ſevere avenger againſt ſuch pretenders.</hi> page 5. and without repentance will be a ſwift witneſſe againſt you, there being in you, even in you ſins againſt the Lord your God committed with this and many other aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating circumſtances.</p>
            <p>For the Lords ſake if you be <hi>Saints,</hi> ſuch as ſhould be grieved at the leaſt riſe of corruption in your ſoules, that ſhould avoid all appearances of evill; Oh let what I have propounded ſtay you in this your ſinnefull progreſſe, that you proceed not to fill up the meaſure of your iniquities.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:164849:15"/>
            <p>Methinks it ſhould move you, if I ſhould be your Remembrancer, but of thoſe miſerable effects that are, or may be the products of your abuſed truſt, and your unwarrantable walking by providence without a precept.</p>
            <p>Should not the glory of God, the honour of his great name be deare unto <hi>you?</hi> Oh my ſoule thou haſt heard the reproach of the adverſary, how are they confirmed in their profaneneſſe and ſuperſtition? in their oppoſition unto the <hi>Reformation</hi> that hath coſt ſo deare, <hi>See,</hi> 
               <q>See, ſay they, how all your hypocriſie is diſcovered, and rather then they ſhall goe unpuniſhed for their rebellion againſt their King, thoſe who were raiſed up to be their <hi>ſaviours,</hi> ſhall be <hi>executioners</hi> of Gods vengeance upon them, and though the Kings Party with his Cavaliers could not be avenged on this City the nurſery of all this Rebellion, yet it ſhall be done by an Army of their owne raiſing.</q> What is more common then ſuch reproaches in the day of our calamity, which you have brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, <hi>And is this nothing unto you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh where I ſay is your zeale for God and his cauſe, which you profeſſe unto? How is the <hi>name of God blaſphemed</hi> amongſt Atheiſts, Papiſts, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, profane and carnall perſons, by your fore-mentioned practiſes, which hath opened their mouths againſt you? how are your friends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided <q>to the peircing of their ſouls, <hi>when they ſay unto them,</hi> Lo are theſe your Saints, your godly and religious party, which held forth nothing but juſtice, &amp; Righteouſneſſe, who were raiſed for the preſervation of the fundamentall Lawes, and of the priviledges of the Parliament, and the liberty of the Subject, and are now riſen up in armes to ruine the King and his poſterity, to deſtroy the Parliament, and give lawes unto the Kingdome; did ever the profaneſt Officers or ſouldiers, under <hi>Eſſex, Waller</hi> or <hi>Maſſey,</hi>
               </q> attempt any of thoſe things which they have effected,</p>
            <p>Oh Sirs ſhould not this be for a lamentation, that inſtead of putting to ſilence, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. the ignorance of fooliſh men, by a conformitie unto thoſe Goſpell precepts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as ſupreame, or unto Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,</hi> You ſhould open their mouths by your evill workes that they behold. Oh Sirs conſider at the laſt theſe true taunts of the adverſary, by which God is diſhonoured, and let them not only pierce your eares, but your hearts.</p>
            <p>Let me further I pray you be your remembrancer of another effect, and a ſad one too, of theſe your preſent practiſes, and that is this.</p>
            <p>That you are not onely thereby caſt out of the eſteeme of Morall men, as walking in ſuch waies that by their <hi>light</hi> doe looke of an ill complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. But alſo out of the approbation of very many tender conſcienced Chriſtians, who <hi>as</hi> they dare not ſay unto you in this your way, we <hi>wiſh
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:164849:15"/>you will in the name of the Lord,</hi> or <hi>bid you God ſpeed,</hi> leaſt they ſhould <hi>be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of your evill deeds,</hi> 2 <hi>John</hi> ver. 11. So they cannot remember you unto God in their prayers, except it be that he would reſtraine you, and hedge up your way with thornes; and is not this a ſad effect indeed. Oh pray Sirs let this conſideration take hold of your hearts, and like <hi>Jeromes Surgite emortuis</hi> be ever ſounding in your eares, both in your <hi>Counſells,</hi> and the execution of <hi>them.</hi> That the arme of fleſh being broken, on which they truſted, that <hi>ſtaffe</hi> (your ſelves) on which they leaned: having peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them and gone into their hands, they have betaken themſelves unto the old and never failing weapons of the Church, <hi>praeces &amp; lachrimae, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>teares;</hi> the mouths of which Cannons being turned againſt you. Which I think though you are good ſouldiers, ſhould ſomewhat affright you, and will, if you are <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> becauſe they are ſpirituall weapons.</p>
            <p>Beſides which, I pray let me remember you of another effect, of your unwarrantable waies in relation unto the publicke, (now it comes in my minde) and thats this, you have juſtified all the jealouſies and feares, that many diſſenting from you, had of you in your minoritie before moddel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing. That if the power of the ſword were wholly put into Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents hands, they would abuſe it for their owne ſelfe intereſt againſt the publicke; have not you juſtified the Cities <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> and their feares in this reſpect, have not you made many ſuppoſed ſcandals in the <hi>Gangre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd</hi> to be but true <hi>predictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſides your juſtification of the feares of many which might fill your faces with ſhame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As</hi> another <hi>effect</hi> of your miſcarrages. Have not <hi>you</hi> blaſted the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſome <hi>eminent</hi> perſons amongſt you, that have <hi>ingaged</hi> for you, either in the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> to our Repreſentatives, That you would rather ſuffer and lay downe your armes at their feet, then breake out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to acts of diſobedience. Or in very publicke, and promiſcuous Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, where there were too many hearers that came for newes, or to make themſelves merry with Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> mimick geſtures, and Pulpit-ſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilities now Plaies are down. I ſay have not you by your fore-mentioned practiſes made Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> a <hi>Lyar</hi> or <hi>worſe,</hi> who ſo often <hi>profeſſed</hi> in your names in the Pulpit, <hi>your readineſſe to lay down your neckes, lives, and to live under rockes and Caves in</hi> America, <hi>rather then not disband, at the leaſt intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parliament, or to doe any act impeaching their Priviledges or proceedings.</hi> I beſeech you all ſeriouſly to conſider this. But <hi>eſpecially</hi> you Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> to whom I have ſpoken all this while in <hi>generall</hi> as one of the Army, though now in particular, as <hi>to one</hi> that notwithſtanding, your former ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the Armies obedience, are now the greateſt hardner of them in this way, not onely by leading them by <hi>providence</hi> into theſe impious
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:164849:16"/>and prepoſterous courſes, by perverting the example of <hi>Phineas,</hi> incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging them in that, for ever to be abhorred force of the Parliament, by the frequent uſe of your ruſtie ſimilitude of a key, made bright again by your often uſe of it, which before would not open the doore, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be forced, but alſo <hi>perſwading</hi> them, that all the oppoſition that is made againſt them in this way, is but for a little holineſſe, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Chriſt in you, Oh Mr. <hi>Peters.</hi> is this good paſture for the Lambs of Chriſt, which he would have you feed as you love him. May not I well ſay unto you, Oh <hi>Archippus,</hi> Col. 2.17. <hi>Take heed unto the miniſtry that thou haſt recived,</hi> not onely <hi>that thou fullfill it.</hi> But that thou <hi>fill it not full,</hi> with ſuch corrupt abuſes of providence, Scripture preſidents, and the partiall urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome Scripture precepts, for carnall ends, as to expoſe the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of your doctrine, to that ruine and calamitie, which as Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> hath obſerved, ſhall riſe over them that are given to change, and yet through your unminiſteriall levitie, and Pulpit ſcurilitie in your geſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and jeans, making your poore ſeduced hearers, like thoſe that are ſtung with the <hi>Tarantula</hi> to die laughing. But <hi>verbum ſapienti,</hi> hoping this <hi>digreſſion</hi> will be pardoned, being led unto it by <hi>providence.</hi> But to return.</p>
            <p>Beſides your juſtification of the fears and jealouſies of many of the godly concerning you. There is a <hi>juſtification</hi> like to be produced as the effect of your preſent practiſes; namely a <hi>juſtification of the wicked,</hi> which is an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination unto the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.15. Even to juſtifie all the Sons of <hi>Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al;</hi> not only ſuch as have been before you in former times, but thoſe that ſhall come after you, to whom you may be a <hi>ſinfull Preſident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe but thinke with your ſelves whether or no, <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> and his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates</hi> traiterous forcing of the Parliament in former times upon <hi>Popular pretences. Henry Jermines, Percies</hi> and <hi>Gorings</hi> Treaſon in practiſing to bring up the Northern Army towards <hi>London</hi> to over-awe and force the Paliament ſoon after its commencement, and the Kings coming to the Commons Houſe with an armed Train of Cavaliers to demand the five Members. <hi>Jan.</hi> 4. 1641. voted to be a <hi>Treaſonable Act,</hi> and an high breach of the <hi>priviledge</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> are not only juſtified but exceeded, by that force and violence offered to the Parliament by you, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 6, 7.</p>
            <p>And yet beſides all this, to be the juſtification as a <hi>Preſident</hi> for any that ſhall perpetrate the like wickedneſſe for the future.</p>
            <p>There is this likewiſe to be weighed as a ſad effect, that <hi>danger</hi> that other <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> may be expoſed unto by your Example, either to be brought under by the Souldierie, that they ſhall raiſe, or elſe to be kept under by Tyrannie which they ſhall rather chooſe, then put a Sword into the hands of any to help them, leſt it ſhould be turned againſt them when they have done their work, <hi>as you have done.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:164849:16"/>
            <p>You ſeem to have a little ſence <hi>page</hi> 34. <hi>Remon.</hi> what will bee the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the ſenſe that will be aptly made, by intelligent Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of this <hi>and neighbour Nations, and ages to come,</hi> of ſome kind of defect in the <hi>Treaty</hi> in regard of the Kings reſtraint in the Iſle of Wight. But dear Chriſtians, you forget that there are intelligent Spectaters of this and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Nations, yea and ages to come, that will have your perfidious practices upon record, and by accident you may be the inſlaving of other free people as well as we, that will rather with <hi>Iſſachar</hi> couch down between their <hi>burthens,</hi> and <hi>become ſervants unto illegall Tribute,</hi> then run the hazard of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them trebled by thoſe whom they truſted to take them off.</p>
            <p>I beſeech <hi>you</hi> therefore if there be any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if there be in <hi>you</hi> any bowels of mercy, any pittie in <hi>you,</hi> towards <hi>your</hi> ſelves, <hi>your</hi> fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, <hi>your</hi> friends, this dying Kingdom, if any zeal for Gods glorie, any ſence of his diſhonour, any love to his people, any true tenderneſſe of conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Make your repentance for your groſſe miſcarriages, as eminent, and as publike, as your ſint.</hi> Let but <hi>Odeds</hi> convincing Interrogation get within <hi>your</hi> conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that there are with <hi>you, even with you,</hi> ſins againſt the Lord your God, under all theſe conſiderations, whereof I have bin your faithfull <hi>remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> and I doubt not but there will be as evident fruits, in the changing of your purpoſes and intentions, as was in thoſe Souldiers in the Hiſtory, and your ſubjection unto the Princes being anſwerable with theirs, may put a ſpeedy end to our troubles, turning our prepoſterous zeal of executing of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon one another, into the execution of thoſe king-like luſts within us that war againſt our ſoules.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe I ſhall go on to be your Remembrancer, of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell that <hi>Oded</hi> exhibited unto the Army, having prepared them for it by his convincing Interrogation, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now hear me therefore, and deliver the Captives again which you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of your Brethren, for the fierce wrath of God is upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hearken unto me</hi> I beſeech you to whom I have directed my diſcourſe, <hi>that God may hearken unto you,</hi> it was the ſpeech of <hi>Iotham</hi> upon a violent change of government, through the effuſion of blood, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.7. Oh hear me, and <hi>deliver the Captives again which you have taken,</hi> ſhew that God hath touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your hearts with a ſence of your ſins, by a ſpeedie imbracing of this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell I now tender unto you.</p>
            <p>I do not call upon <hi>you</hi> to deliver up any of your <hi>priſoners</hi> of <hi>war,</hi> which are of your Brethren Engliſh or Scots, although here is a good call ſomewhat like it, the Lord himſelf teaching you how to bee differenced in your carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in a time of war towards Bretheren and Forrainers.</p>
            <p>But deliver thoſe Captives that <hi>you</hi> have taken without any Commiſſion, but the abuſe of that power put into <hi>your</hi> hands.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:164849:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Set the King at liberty, deliver him up into thoſe hands, out of which you took him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know that this may be recented as a Malignant motion, but having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>you</hi> my ground for it, and anſwered <hi>yours</hi> againſt it, it will appear other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>your</hi> arguments againſt the Covenant in that part of it, as not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually <hi>obliging the taker to endeavour the preſervation of the Kings Perſon and authority:</hi> I muſt confeſſe that having ſeriouſly weighed them, I find them to be but as broken reeds, that will <hi>peirce</hi> thoſe with <hi>perjury,</hi> that lean upon them, and therefore I dare not.</p>
            <p>Whereas you ſay that <hi>this Covenant</hi> as it is drawne hath not left the takers without an honeſt way out, <hi>page</hi> 54. I grant it, if you mean only of this Article in relation to the preſervation of the Kings perſon, with the reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is expreſſed in the ſame Covenant, to preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties perſon and Authority, in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion and liberties of the Kingdome. But not to preſerve and defend the Kings perſon and Authority, when he is in the way to all theſe, as was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in the laſt free vote of the Houſe, in reference to his laſt Meſſage, but rather to make him vile, and ſeek the deſtruction of his Perſon; Is ſuch a breath of Covenant, and diſ-loyalty, that <hi>the</hi> (world) <hi>that we call to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with our Conſciences of our loyalty, and that we have no thoughts, and intentions to diminiſh his juſt power and greatneſſe, muſt needs take notice of our perfideous trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, as men to be abhorred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now as you affirme, <hi>p.</hi> 54. that if the Covenant had not been drawn up that <hi>yet through the providence of God the ſnare is broken, and they may eſcape.</hi> Though it be a very ſtrange thing, yet I doe not much wonder, that you aſcribe perjurie unto Gods providence. Saying the ſnare is broken by the providence of God, or as God hath ordered the buſineſſe <hi>pag.</hi> 51. it doth not now obliege you before God or Man. I ſay I doe not much wonder, that you ſhould grant a <hi>diſpenſation</hi> for perjurie, calling it an honeſt way to get out of an oath, which is the maine pillar of humaine ſociety, with ſecuritie and ſafetie, when that to procure a Toleration for ſins as griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſpirit of truth, you care not for ſhaking the pillars of the land, and breaking the beautifull ſtaves of magiſtracy and miniſtry aſunder.</p>
            <p>As for your argument of nulling the Covenant, as to the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kings perſon, upon his refuſall to take it, there being no mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall agreement, It may have an eaſie inervation.</p>
            <p>If it were as you ſuppoſe, nay confidently affirme it to be a <hi>Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man in the civill parts of it,</hi> pag. 57. there were ſome ſtrength in your <hi>argument,</hi> but it is <hi>clear,</hi> that the Covenant is between God and man, for it was with a hand lifted up to the moſt high God that wee did
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:164849:17"/>ſwear, and not unto man, that wee did ingage our ſelves, and therefore there is more in it then the <hi>calling of God to witneſſe the truth of our intentions</hi> pag. 59. For it is not ſaid, that we did ſwear with our hands lifted up <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> the moſt high God; but <hi>to</hi> the moſt high God: hee it was to whom we did ſweare, and with whom we did enter into <hi>Covenant,</hi> and that in the <hi>civill parts of it,</hi> that we might be the more ſtrongly ingaged by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to doe what wee were bound unto by the law of God, which war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants every article in it, and this of the preſervation of the Kings Perſon with the reſtriction, And therefore the Kings not taking the Covenant, or agreement with it, is of no more force to abſolve the taker of it from perjury, and breach of Covenant with God, Then if a perſon ſencible of ſtrong temptation to take away his fathers life, ſhould therefore make a Vow and Covenant that he would (according to his duty) preſerve it, and yet after the ſame to conclude <hi>diſ-ingagement</hi> in the ſight of God, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his fathers not agreement with him in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Which I humbly conceive is the caſe of our <hi>pater patriae, de jure</hi> though not <hi>de facto.</hi> And that the ſtate in the drawing up of that part of the ſaid Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant were not, either without a ſenſe of ſome ſtrong temptation to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loialtie, Or more then ordinary carefull to prevent the ſcandall of it from the world is evident, therefore did ſo draw it up, as more ſolemnly to ingage the taker to the preſervation of the Kings Perſon, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with the reſtriction, then to anyother part of the Covenant, and they adde that by keeping the Covenant in this point, according to the reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, we may ſatisfie the <hi>world,</hi> which they <hi>imply</hi> was jealous of them, and therefore in the Covenant it runs, that although the world bee not called to witneſſe for us in relation to any other article in the Covenant, yet to this of the preſervation and defence of the Kings Majeſties perſon, and authority, in the preſervation of the true Religion, and the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Kingdome, we appeale to the whole world, <hi>That the world may beare witneſſe with our Conſciences of our loyalty, and that we have no thoughts or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to deminiſh his Majeſties juſt power and greatneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now before I leave the Covenant, I ſhall onely be your <hi>Remembrancer</hi> once againe, of your owne Chaplaines opinion in this point of breach of <hi>Covenant,</hi> who having charged you with it, in relation unto the Kings perſon, <hi>pag.</hi> 39. hear what he ſaith of <hi>you, juſt Remon.</hi> pag. 41. That you are <hi>not</hi> onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>accuſers, and at this you</hi> are <hi>exquiſite.</hi> But <hi>Truce-breakers</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>againſt accommodation, no Treaty nor agreement, or breakers of Covenant.</hi> and he addes <hi>Solemne Oathes and Covenants are able to hold moſt mens conſciences, but men heightened by Religion into the formes of the ſpirit, doing things by immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate direction from God, carrying a glorious preſence of God before them, affirming that they are called by God to do ſome eſpeciall worke, in the world, theſe can eaſily
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:164849:18"/>mount above the higheſt ſorts of oathes: Men that have taſted of theſe high things, and begin to make them ſerviceable to worldly ends, they are ſuch cunning Pick-locks that they can find the way through any doores, to come to the treaſures of power and authority.</hi> And then he goeth on in the ſame page, <hi>lines</hi> 30. <hi>Such wicked ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are now abroad like thoſe,</hi> Ezek. 21.31. <hi>Brutiſh men, skilfull to deſtroy.</hi> Brutiſh, <hi>ſpare not the holieſt nor honourableſt things, Kings, Lords, Miniſters, Scripture-Ordinances, Oathes, Covenants, lay all waſte, and yet in the greateſt brutiſhneſſe.</hi> Skillfull, <hi>though there be the moſt ſenſuall, and beaſtly Confuſion, yet they ſhall doe it artificially,</hi> skilfully, <hi>ſay tis for God, Juſtice, Religion, and that they doe it by the power of Chriſt, and the power of God in Religious zeal.</hi> And becauſe that he hath another aphoriſme which may well be referred without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependencie to this common place that I am now upon, as you ſhall find written, Printed I ſhould ſay, for <hi>your</hi> inſtruction, <hi>pag.</hi> 37. Juſt Remon. <hi>See how abhominable Religion is when once corrupted, there are no kind of men can be ſuch compleate, and new knaves, as a Jeſuite, a Phariſee, an old well ſtudied pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Religion, when once mens Conſciences are defiled, and they begin to trade in the world, with a pretence that tis for God, they are ſo cunning, that no bonds of honeſty, or faith can poſſibly hold them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ceaſing to remember you any further of your Chaplin, of whom I ſhall take my leave, with this Encomium, that had he bin as infallible in his opinion of the <hi>generall</hi> day of Judgement, as he will be taken to be in thoſe quotations that doe concerne you, we had not then ſeene thoſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes that are like to come upon the Kingdom by your meanes.</p>
            <p>I returne to the occaſion of my diſcourſe upon the Covenant, with which one <hi>buſh</hi> I hope I have ſtopped two <hi>gaps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the <hi>way</hi> anſwering what you have alleaged to the enervation of that article in the Covenant, <hi>the preſervation of the Kings perſon and authority,</hi> and <hi>conſequently</hi> evincing that, for me to move it, or you to follow it, namely to ſet the Kings perſon at libertie, to treat with his Parliament. That ſo your great feares: of nulling all his grants, and conceſſions upon the plea of his reſtraint may be taken away, is no malignant motion or breach of covenant.</p>
            <p>I know that you doe anticipate this <hi>motion</hi> by a repreſentation very large in your Remonſtrance, <hi>of the unjuſtneſſe and ſafeneſſe of a Treaty with him,</hi> (which is already anſwered in ſhort.) But in the ſtead thereof that rather his <hi>Perſon</hi> ſhould be brought to <hi>juſtice.</hi> For which you have <hi>two</hi> ſtrong arguments, the one you often uſe, <hi>God</hi> having <hi>given him ſo clearely into your power to doe juſtice,</hi> page 24. and ſeverall other places. But I hope if you doe but conſider ſeriouſly how you came by him (of which I have remembred you already,) you will uſe that argument no more.</p>
            <p>The other becauſe that you finde <hi>that his heart</hi> which in a more eſpeciall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:164849:18"/>manner is in the hand of God <hi>is not changed,</hi> page 24.56. Therefore you will cut off his head, as ſtrange a cure for a hard heart, as are your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions from the premiſes aforeſaid. But I wonder not much at them, when you make a profeſſion of the <hi>light</hi> you goe by, <hi>viz. reaſon,</hi> or <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the ordinary lights men are in humane things to walke by,</hi> Remon. page 45. 46. But doth not this ſhow that you are carnall and walke as men, for our reaſon and experience, even in <hi>humane things</hi> are to be denied, if we walke as Saints, rather then run upon an <hi>appearance of evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to cleare it, I ſhall give you an inſtance of a Saint, who in your judgement was given up <hi>unto a prepoſterous and ſelfe deſerting courſe,</hi> page 27. walking not by carnall reaſon or experience, no nor yet by providence without precept, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.3. King <hi>Saul</hi> was by the providence of God put into <hi>Davids</hi> hand, and that ſo <hi>clearely,</hi> as that his ſouldiers led by reaſon, told him in effect, that God had delivered him into his hand to do juſtice on him, ver. 4. But did <hi>David</hi> make uſe of his carnall reaſon. If I now cut him off, I ſhall be ſecure and ſafe from his further purſuite of me for my life, and I ſhall attaine unto the Crowne, a ſtrong temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? No, his tender conſcience ſmote him but for cutting off the Kings garment, though but to convince his enemy that he might as eaſily have cut off his head, ver. 11. and not only ſo, but from the ſame tenderneſſe of conſcience he would not be acceſſary unto the ſinne of his ſervants, who it ſeemes being ruled only by their carnall reaſon, were ready to riſe up againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> had not this Saint by arguments impeded them, ver. 7. And <hi>ſo David ſtayed his ſervants with theſe words, and ſuffered them not to riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Saul.</hi> But what were thoſe words, ver. 6. and he ſaid to his men, the Lord forbid that I ſhould doe this thing unto my maſter the Lords anointed to ſtretch forth my hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But yet further, as you ſee he would not walke by reaſon as a man, ſo neither would he walke by his <hi>experience</hi> againſt the <hi>rule;</hi> for though he had found by experience, that the King being ſet at liberty did ſtill purſue his life, as you find, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.26. Yet when providence had brought him into his hand againe, though <hi>Abiſhai</hi> told him, <hi>God hath delivered thine enemy into thy hand this day, now therefore let me ſmite him,</hi> providence hath preſented me with a weapon, his owne Speare. But did <hi>David</hi> as a man walke by his <hi>experience,</hi> he finds by experience <hi>Saul</hi> ſtill thirſting after his blood, and might not he have reaſoned ſo. I find no inward conviction, remorſe, or change of heart and principles, <hi>rationally appearing in him,</hi> page 56. he is ſo farre from being ſorry for what he hath done already, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding my ingenuity in ſparing his life before, that he is reſileſſe in his purſuite of me, and therefore it would not onely be full of viſible
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:164849:19"/>danger and unſafe, but it may prove certainely deſtructive to me, if I ſhould goe againſt my <hi>experience</hi> and let him goe. I will now therefore be led by <hi>reaſon, experience,</hi> and by <hi>providence,</hi> and execute <hi>juſtice</hi> upon my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable adverſary. But if you conſult with the ſtory, you ſhall finde that he would neither do it himſelfe, or incourage any other. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtaieth and diverts <hi>Abiſhai</hi> from the ſame, by this divine prohibition, which the Lord bring home to your hearts. ver. 9. And <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Abiſhai, deſtroy him not;</hi> in your language, execute not <hi>juſtice upon him,</hi> and what is his reaſon, <hi>who can ſtretch forth his hand against the Lords anointed and be guilteſſe,</hi> ver. 10. <hi>David ſaid furthermore, as the Lord liveth, the Lord he ſhall ſmite him, Or his day ſhall come to dye,</hi> Or he ſhall deſcend into battell and periſh, ver. 11. the Lord forbid that <hi>I ſhould ſtretch forth my hands againſt the Lords anointed.</hi> Let me be your <hi>Obſervator</hi> here I beſeech you, what diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, either as a <hi>principall,</hi> or <hi>acceſſary,</hi> from walking at this time by the <hi>ordinary light</hi> of <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>experience?</hi> do but peruſe his <hi>Arguments,</hi> and you ſhall finde in them that though his <hi>feare</hi> and ſence of <hi>guilt</hi> was in the <hi>front,</hi> yet his <hi>faith</hi> and confidence in God brought up the <hi>reare,</hi> for you ſhall finde him there, not uſing his <hi>ſenſe</hi> but his faith, which he did act upon the <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of God with moſt admired confidence, <hi>concluding</hi> that though he <hi>uſe</hi> no ſuch ſinnefull meanes for <hi>ſelfe-preſervation,</hi> yet he ſolemnly <hi>aſſerts</hi> as <hi>the Lord liveth,</hi> that either the Lord would ſmite him <hi>immediately,</hi> or if not, he ſhould ſhortly end his daies according to the <hi>courſe of nature,</hi> or that he ſhould come to a <hi>caſuall end.</hi> Oh Sirs, you that doe profeſſe your ſelves to be <hi>Saints</hi> as <hi>David,</hi> walke not by reaſon, or providence without or againſt a precept; behold his <hi>conſident perſwaſion,</hi> that God had waies enough to <hi>free</hi> him from his <hi>potent Adverſary,</hi> but by no ſinnefull ſhifts or pretences would he <hi>free</hi> himſelfe; <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>ſelfe-love</hi> were both <hi>mortified</hi> in him, let them be ſo in <hi>you</hi> if you are <hi>Saints</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. His <hi>faith</hi> did ſubjugate his <hi>carnall reaſon</hi> and <hi>experience.</hi> Oh ſhow that, that <hi>precious grace</hi> is not dead at the roote in you, but ſtirre up thoſe <hi>ſparkes</hi> of it that are ready to <hi>goe out,</hi> that it may breake out into a <hi>flame,</hi> and walke by the <hi>light</hi> of that, and not of <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>experience, the ordinary lights that men walke by.</hi> That ſo you who are but private perſons, that were never <hi>called</hi> or <hi>choſen</hi> for thoſe ſervices in which you are now ſo ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, <hi>nor</hi> to cry for <hi>juſtice</hi> upon the grounds already mentioned by Mr. <hi>Sedgwick;</hi> may deſiſt from theſe <hi>conſcience</hi>-waſting, and land-<hi>deſolating</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of yours, and <hi>putting your truſt in the Lord,</hi> you <hi>leane</hi> no more <hi>unto your own underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude therefore the Counſell given in relation to the King, with a point of Doctrine Collected by Maſter <hi>Henry Burton,</hi> who being <hi>dead yet ſpeaketh in his booke for God and the King,</hi> p. 44. where from his afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:164849:19"/>Text he raiſeth this point of Doctrine. <hi>That the true fear of a King, as it is a filiall fear, ſo it is a fear of adherency, a fear full of loyalty and fidelity, which makes a true Subject to ſtick ſo cloſe to his Prince at all times, and in all conditions, as nothing ſhall make a ſeparation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, as I would deſire <hi>you</hi> to <hi>heare mee,</hi> and deliver up your <hi>Captived</hi> King. So likewiſe I beſeech you heare me now, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver up again <hi>your Captives</hi> of the <hi>Parliament men,</hi> for if to retaine <hi>priſoners</hi> of warre that are <hi>brethren</hi> as <hi>Captives,</hi> may expoſe an <hi>Army</hi> unto the fierce wrath of <hi>God,</hi> as appeareth in this <hi>hiſtory,</hi> 2 Chron. 28.21. <hi>Now heare me therefore, and deliver the Captives again; which you have taken captive of your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for the fierce wrath of God is upon you.</hi> For this (was ſpoken to the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> that <hi>ſucceſſefull Army</hi>) Oh what divine vengeance? and fiery indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is like to fall upon <hi>you,</hi> without <hi>repentance</hi> for the <hi>violence you</hi> offered unto the perſons of ſo many godly, and ſincere <hi>aſſertors</hi> of the Subjects libertie, and the Kingdomes <hi>good.</hi> If to offend but one of <hi>Chriſts little ones</hi> may expoſe a perſon to a condition more <hi>eligible</hi> then to <hi>have a milſtone hanged about his necke, and be drowned in the depth of the Sea, Mat.</hi> 18.6. I ſay, if to offend but one <hi>little one</hi> may prove ſo dreadfull to the offendor, what then to offend an eminent <hi>Sufferer</hi> for the <hi>Publick, a ſtrong man in Chriſt,</hi> that could ſuffer 8 years impriſonment (4 of them cloſe, 3 in exile) three Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lories, with the loſſe of eares, calling, and eſtate, for the publicke good both in relation to Church and State. And I beſeech you conſider, doe you thinke that you did not offend him, when you ſeized forcibly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his perſon going to the <hi>Houſe</hi> to diſcharge his duty, haled him violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thence into the <hi>Queenes Court,</hi> notwithſtanding his proteſtation of breach of priviledge, and a double demand of the Houſe (that raiſed you) for his preſent inlargement. Doe you thinke you did not <hi>offend</hi> him when you carried him priſoner to Hell, and there ſhut him up all night without any lodging or other accommodations, keeping him ſtill pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, deprived of his liberty and calling, without <hi>objecting</hi> the <hi>leaſt cauſe</hi> for this your unjuſt reſtraint? Oh that God would but convince you both of your ſinne and danger. Not only in relation to that moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Martyr and true Philopater, who hath ſolemnly <hi>declared this and more then I have charged upon you, before the moſt juſt and righteous God of Heaven and Earth, the ſearcher of all hearts, the whole Kingdome, Engliſh Nation, and the World,</hi> in his declaration ſubſcribed <hi>William Prynne, Decem.</hi> 26. 1648. But alſo in relation to the violence and offence offered unto, not that one, but many godly and ſincere Patriots; for I cannot thinke but that there are many ſuch amongſt thoſe impriſoned and ſecluded Members, being (above one hundred in number) which I beſeech you let not ſeeme <hi>a</hi> ſmall ſinne, no ſinne in your ſight. If that you <hi>call</hi> the <hi>Kings attempt</hi> in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:164849:20"/>his <hi>proceedings againſt the Members bee impeached, that appeared to aſſert</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon liberties, againſt his intereſt to <hi>witneſſe</hi> his <hi>revenge,</hi> page 31 Oh what may be ſaid not only for your bold attempt, but unparalel'd execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that violence upon the perſons of many that appeared in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> to ſticke faſt unto their firſt principles or the publique, againſt your <hi>intereſt</hi> of <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Tolleration,</hi> loaden with unchriſtian reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>rotten Members, Apoſtates,</hi> and ſuch as drive private deſignes.</p>
            <p>But do you thinke the <hi>ſearcher of all hearts</hi> can be <hi>blinded,</hi> as you would doe the Kingdome, who now ſee into the ground of that violence offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the perſons of their Repreſentatives, and ſecluding them from the Houſe, That ſo thoſe whom you have thought fitting to ſet there, may vote and unvote what you would have them, and do <hi>you</hi> think that the righteous judge of the whole world will not declare againſt <hi>you</hi> by ſome viſible tokens of his diſpleaſure for theſe things, was the fierce wrath of God upon the Souldiery in this Hiſtory, for their cruell intentions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their brethren, and ſhall you eſcape? Aſſure your ſelves if that God loves you, he will rebuke and chaſten you: and wil make you know that it is an evil thing and a bitter to walk in ſuch ways as are ſo unwarrantable, and unſuitable to your profeſſion.</p>
            <p>And therefore now I beſeech you hearken unto me, that God may hearken unto you, <hi>Set the members at liberty that you have reſtrained,</hi> declare your hearty ſorrow and repentance, for <hi>thoſe ſinnes that are in you, even in you against the Lord your God,</hi> of which I have bin your Remembrancer. <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> your unfeined <hi>purpoſes</hi> and <hi>reſolutions</hi> to <hi>meddle</hi> no more out of your <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> with the affaires of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> with which you were never <hi>intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> But that you with other <hi>Subjects</hi> will acquieſſe, with what ſhall be concluded betweene King and Parliament: And no queſtion but upon your deſire of <hi>pardon</hi> for what hath been done againſt them, you ſhall find that according to the <hi>injunction</hi> given them by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> they will be as willing to <hi>forgive</hi> and <hi>forget,</hi> as you ſhall be to <hi>deſire</hi> it, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.2.3.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe this <hi>motion</hi> may ſeeme to <hi>Carnall Politicians</hi> to be very redicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and like the maker of it, <hi>very weake</hi> and <hi>ſimple.</hi> But if ever you would enter upon a worke without <hi>conſulting with fleſh and blood,</hi> next to your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, doe it now, to ſave the Kingdome; if you debate this motion in the <hi>Court</hi> of carnall reaſon, it will be caſt over the barre, and want of its <hi>due</hi> recentment and acceptance. But if the Lord by his convincing ſpirit, through thoſe convincing interrogations which I have propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhall but awaken your conſciences, as he wrought upon thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men in the <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> by <hi>Odeds</hi> unexpected coming out to meet them. I ſhould then <hi>hope</hi> all carnall and fleſhly <hi>reaſonings</hi> being denyed, you would prove <hi>as</hi> imitable a preſident to <hi>future generations,</hi> as I deſire that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:164849:20"/>in the Hiſtory may prove a <hi>convincing</hi> paterne to you.</p>
            <p>Upon a <hi>ſound conviction</hi> that army was changed in their <hi>purpoſes,</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up their <hi>Captives,</hi> forſooke their <hi>ſpoyle,</hi> and <hi>ſubmitted</hi> to their <hi>Princes.</hi> Oh that God by what I have propounded to worke this ſound convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would make it effectuall. Then would you deliver up your Captives, ſubmit to your Princes, and that blacke and bloody cloud of raine and confuſion that is like to come upon you and the Kingdome, would be ſcattered.</p>
            <p>And let me adde thus much further, that if to what hath beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Lord ſhall graciouſly incline your hearts: As you ſhall ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by revive the hearts of this dying Kingdome, with hopes of a joyfull accommodation betweene the King and Parliament, which for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is only <hi>interrupted by your meanes.</hi> I make no queſtion but as you ſhall finde the Lord <hi>accompliſhing</hi> his promiſe to you, <hi>that when a mans wayes pleaſe the Lord he will make his enemies to be at peace with him.</hi> So likewiſe ſtirring up the <hi>hearts</hi> both of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> to grant you that <hi>liberty of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that Christ hath purchaſed for you;</hi> and not only ſo, but giving you ſuch favour in their eyes, as ſtill to be continued in ſuch numbers, and for ſuch time as ſhall be thought convenient for the publique ſafety; and that for your maintenance the people will chearefully pay their Taxes, when they are but in ſome hopes of a comfortable end of all their troubles.</p>
            <p>Weigh this I beſeech you, and conſider that there are many thouſands, that although they cannot <hi>cloſe with you</hi> or <hi>approve</hi> of your ſinfull waies, yet would be exceeding ſad, to ſee any of you that are the eminent Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Commanders of this Army, or the Souldiery either, That have done ſuch gallant ſervice as Souldiers, expoſed unto ſuch a miſerable condition as this courſe you are in, doth inevitably tend unto: We would willingly <hi>ſave you</hi> and pluck you as <hi>firebrands</hi> out of the fire, reſcue you from that ſentence of <hi>death,</hi> that your unwarrantable <hi>actions</hi> have poſſed upon you. We would ſay of you who are the <hi>Jonathans,</hi> the Worthy Commanders of the Army, <hi>Shall</hi> Jonathan <hi>dye that hath wrought this great ſalvation in Iſrael, God forbid,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.15. But Oh do not you by ſhutting your eares againſt the <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> now given you, <hi>destroy</hi> your ſelves and become your own executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, expoſe the Kingdome to perpetuall <hi>wars</hi> both <hi>ſorreign</hi> and <hi>intestine:</hi> Which that it may be prevented, do not ſtudy how to <hi>evade</hi> any Arguments that I have preſented before you for your <hi>conviction, that there are in you, even in you ſins againſt the Lord your God. But</hi> follow the <hi>example</hi> of theſe <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> here in the Hiſtory, leave <hi>arguing</hi> againſt <hi>them,</hi> and fall to <hi>acting;</hi> and let me but humbly adde one thing more. That if you ſhall but <hi>find your hearts</hi> inclining to the counſell and advice that I have <hi>laia before you;</hi> and that this <hi>Scripture Expedient</hi> hath taken hold of your hearts.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:164849:21"/>
            <p>That you as Saints and Chriſtians, as plainly and lovingly would admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſame <hi>Phyſick</hi> to the City. There is no queſtion but you with <hi>Oded</hi> may ſay unto them: Are there not with <hi>you, even with you,</hi> ſins againſt the Lord your God, and that not only <hi>abſolutely</hi> but in <hi>relation</hi> to <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and that the City with humilitie and due reſpects may tender the ſame <hi>expedient</hi> unto the Parliament to whom no doubt it may be ſaid, as unto the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Governours in this Hiſtorie, <hi>Are there not with you, even with you ſins againſt the Lord your God,</hi> and they likewiſe may preſent it unto the King who ſtands in need of a convincing Interrogation alſo.</p>
            <p>Which Scripture Expedient being ſincerely and cordially laid before each other out of Principles of Love, and an unfained deſire of Reconciliation, that there may be no more diſterences amongſt us that are Brethren by ſo many bonds. We according to the Goſpel-precept, <hi>Confeſſing our ſins one unto another, and praying one for another,</hi> James 5.16. We who have ſo woful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounded one another, with wounds of all ſorts and kinds, <hi>we may be healed</hi> and may find the Lord graciouſly returning unto his <hi>Jeruſalem, healing us with revealing abundance of Peace and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus hoping by what I have preſented before you, I ſhall adminiſter occaſion to you to make uſe of <hi>Davids benediction,</hi> 1 Sam. 25.32. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord, which hath ſent thee this day to meet us, and bleſſed be thy advice, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be thou which haſt kept us this day from coming to ſhed blood, from avenging our ſelves with our own hands.</hi> And that I ſhall receive as comfortable an Anſwer from you, as did that weak inſtrument, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>Goe up in peace to thy houſe, for we have hearkened to thy voice, and have accepted of thy perſon.</hi> We look not upon the weaknes or the unworthineſſe of the Inſtrument, nor any failings of his in the delivery of his mind in the diſcharge of his Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Which aforeſaid favour I doe the more importunately deſire, being conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to my ſelf of my own weakneſſe and diſ-abillity for this Service, which though I might have bin helped againſt by <hi>conſulting</hi> with ſome of the godly and learned Miniſtry in it, yet I purpoſely declined the ſame, knowing your <hi>prejudice</hi> againſt them, as thoſe which trouble your <hi>Babel.</hi> Thus hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeching the Lord to give the <hi>Comforter</hi> to be your <hi>Convincer.</hi> I leave you to the ſerious conſideration of what I have ſaid, and the Lord give you underſtanding.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 13.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But if you will not hear it, my ſoul ſhall weep in ſecret for your pride.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
